好的，欢迎回来。感谢大家的到来，我们现在开始吧。
Okay. Welcome back. Thanks for coming, and let's get started.
首先，PA三已经发布了。
So first, PA three is posted.
如果你查看GitHub，会看到有一个p三文件夹。
If you check GithHub there's a p three folder.
我认为助教们会跟进发帖通知。
I think the TAs will follow up with post.
好的，但这张幻灯片给了你一个概览。
Okay. But this slide gives you an overview.
我们有四个问题，第一个问题是MOE。
We have four questions. The first question, MOE.
这其实是PA二最后一个问题的延续。
Okay? It's basically a continuation of the last question in PA two.
在P二中，你们用或归约实现了TP Ter pl。
In P two, you use or reduced to TP Ter pl.
这里我让你们用all to all来做MOE，就这样。
And here I ask you to use all to all to do MOE. Okay? That's it.
是的，关于m inference有一个稍微难一点的问题。
Yeah. There's a slightly more difficult one on m inference.
如果你看看这个，基本上，
If you take a look at this basically,
我希望你能实现推测性解码。
I'd like you to implement speculative decoding.
好的，我下周会讲这个内容。
Okay, I will cover that next week.
然后，就像我承诺的，嗯，基本上有两个编程作业，我们还有一个
And then, like I promised, um, that are basically two programming assignment, and we have one more
稍微偏理论的作业。
slightly more theoretical assignment.
斯金纳定律，好吗？我会让你，我会给你
Skinning law, okay? I'm going to let you I'm going to give
几美元，让你设计你自己的IM，也就是计算机最优的，
you a few dollars and ask you to design your own IM, which is computer optimal,
这个我今天会讲，好吗？
which I will cover today, okay?
所以你有空间去设计你自己的RM，好吗？
So you have the space to design your own RM, okay?
而且我认为你不需要写很多代码。
And I don't think you need to write a lot of code.
这只是一些辅助你探索设计空间的函数，仅此而已。
It's just a few passing function to help you navigate the design space. That's it.
是的。最后，我让你写一篇作文，大约500字。
Yeah. And lastly, I ask you to write an essay, and it's basically 500 words.
你可以写任何你想写的内容。
And you can write whatever you want.
我希望你能够表达一个坚定的观点。
And I want you to basically make a conviction.
在你上完这门课后，我希望你能为你的观点辩护，好吗？
And after you take this course, and I hope you can argue your conviction, okay?
这基本上就是最后一个要求了。
That is basically the last one.
好的，纯粹的作文，纯粹的写作。
Okay, pure essay, pure writing.
好的，太好了。我想助教会在这里发一条通知。
Okay, cool. I think TA will follow up with a post here.
好的，我们继续吧。
Okay. Let's continue.
我想我们快要讲完并行性这一部分了，对吧？
I think we are about to finish parallelism, right?
我们来谈谈自动并行化。
We talk about autoparalization.
我觉得我基本上提到了两类问题。
I think I basically mentioned two categories of matters.
一类是基于学习的。
One is learning based.
好的，强化学习。
Okay, reinforced learning.
这种方法非常蛮力，基本上是在搜索PLIS设计空间，
It's very brute force that you basically, search the plis design space and
你试图获得一些奖励信号，然后训练一个模型。
you try to get some reward signal, and you train a model.
第二类是基于优化的，基本上就是Opa，我们继续回顾一下Opa。
The second is the optimization based, which is basically Opa and let's continue Opa to recap.
在Opa中，我们基本上会给定一个连续的图和设备集群。
I Opa we basically are given continue graph and device cluster.
我们会进行两次遍历，以找出最优的并行策略。
And we take two passes, to find out the optimal pattern strategy.
我们之所以设计两次遍历，是因为一次遍历是不可能完成的。
The reason we design two passes is because it's impossible to do it in one pass.
这太难了，好吗？
It's too difficult, okay?
有一些启发式方法我们可以利用，因为就像我说的，互操作更倾向于，
And there are some heuristics that we can nverag because like I said, interop prefers,
比如说，低带宽通信和之前的高带宽通信。
like, low bondis communication and the previous high bodice communication.
所以我们基本上可以把第一遍映射到节点之间，第二遍
So we can basically map the first path across nodes and the second pass
在节点内部用Milink来实现，好吗？
inside of the node using Milink, okay?
这基本上就是利用了，嗯，你知道的，现在的硬件特性，好吗？
That is basically leveraging, um, you know, hardware properties today, okay?
所以基本上，我们就是这样组织的。
So basically, we do this kind of organization.
我们首先，把我们的设备集群分成几个，我称之为子匹配，好吗？
We first, um, split our device cluster into a few which I call sub matches, okay?
然后我们也把神经网络分成不同的阶段，
And then we also split our neural network into different stages,
然后我们把阶段映射到匹配上，好吗。
and we map the stage to matches, okay.
然后在映射之后，我们基本上会执行intrap路径，这一步是试图弄清楚
And then after the mapping, we basically perform the intrap path, which is trying to figure out
给定阶段和网格的情况下，最优的intrapb策略是什么。
the optimal intrapb strategy given stage and mesh.
我们会不断地枚举，不断地枚举，对吧？
And we keep enumerating keep enumerating, okay?
接着我们开始提出这个问题。
And then we start asking the problem.
那么我们到底应该如何解决这个自动化问题，对吧？
So how exactly should we solve this oomation, right?
那我们来看看每一步，好吗？
So let's take a look at each pass, okay?
所以在interop这一步，实际上我们是在解决流水线划分的问题。
So so in the interop pass, essentially, we are trying to solve for pipeline partism?
问题在于我们想把图划分成不同的阶段，并且我们想找到一种方式
The problem is that we want to split the graph into stages and we want to find a way
能够最大程度地减少流水线执行的延迟。
that basically minimize the pipeline execution agency.
在这里，我们做了一个非常现实的假设，就是我们已经知道了流水线的调度。
Okay. Here, we make a very realistic assumption, that is, we already know the pipeline schedule.
比如说，你可能知道我们大概会采用F和B，或者非常类似的东西，对吧？
For example, you probably know we probably adopt one F and B or something very similar, right?
因为其他的调度方式可能行不通。
Because other schedule probably don't work.
F TPP行不通，是的。
F TPP doesn't work, yeah.
所以我们大概就会说，我们要用，呃，WY F和B。
And we probably just say, we are going to use, um WY F and B.
在这种情况下，我们的问题本质上就是
And given that, our problem is essentially we try to
想办法把新的网络分开，对吧？
figure out a way that split the new networks, right?
如果你还记得，呃，当我们尝试拆分新网络时，我们的目标是什么。
So if you still remember, uh, when we try to split new network, what's our goal.
我们要确保每个阶段大致需要相同的时间来执行，对吧？
We try to make sure that each stage takes roughly the same time to acute, right?
因为如果有慢节点的话，整个流水线调度
Because if there's a straggler, then the entire pipeline schedule
就会被这个慢节点拖慢。
is going to be slowed down, by the straggler.
所以这基本上就是我们的问题，对吧。
So this is basically our problem, right.
所以我们尝试把它分成A、B、C、D四个阶段，我们也尝试从整个设备集群中分离出来。
So we try to split into A B CD four stages, and we also try to split
也就是说，我们从整个设备集群中匹配出来。
a match from the entire device cluster.
所以我们要确保当某个阶段被分配到那个匹配时，它基本上和其他阶段同时进行。
So we make sure that stage when it is assigned on that match, it basically exceed with
也就是说，和其他阶段在同一时间进行，对吧？
other stages with the same time as other stages, okay?
这里我引入一些符号。
And here I introduce a few notation.
比如说，T1、T2、T3，
For example, T one, T two, T three,
基本上就是当我把一个阶段分配给一个匹配时的筛选时间，
I basically a screening time when I assign a stage to a match,
你可以看到，如果我画出这个扫描图，
you can see, if I draw this scan chart,
我基本上就是写下了这个方程。
I basically uh write down this equation.
我发现整个流水线筛选的延迟基本上由两个部分组成。
I find that uh the entire Pipeline screening latency basically is composed of two terms.
第一个部分，我称之为预热阶段。
The first term which I call warmup phase.
也就是说，当我刚开始时，流水线还没有形成，
That is basically when I just get started, my pipeline is not formed yet,
但我已经开始输入批次数据。
but I start feeding batches.
在这种情况下，我有一个预热阶段，
I have a warm up phase which is basically in this case,
T一加d二加T三加34。
T one plus d two plus T three plus 34.
然后我有第二个阶段，也就是稳定阶段。
And then I have a second phase, which is stable phase.
这时我的流水线已经准备就绪。
That is my pipeline is ready form.
我有无限的批次流，对吧？
I have infinite stream of batches, right?
然后我再加上第二项。
And then I add a second term.
第二项非常简单。
And the second term is very easy.
它基本上由最慢的阶段决定。
It is basically determined by the slowest stage.
明白了吗？所以我有第二项，对吧？
Okay? So I have a second term, okay?
本质上，我是在尝试解决这个问题。
Essentially, I'm trying to solve this obit.
所以如果你做过一点算法，你可能知道这个算法可以通过
So if you do a little bit algorithm, you probably know this algorithm can be solved using
一个非常典型的动态规划方法来解决，对吧？
a a very typical dynamic programming approach, okay?
你可以想象，什么时候这个值最小？
And you can imagine, when is this one minimized?
基本上就是当所有阶段都相等的时候，对吧？
It's basically when all the stages, um, are equal, right?
所以我们基本上可以枚举所有可能的网格划分和阶段划分，并且我们不断使用
So we can basically enumerate all those possible mesh split and stages split, and we keep using
动态规划来剪枝空间，最终我们会得到一个给定的解决方案
dynamic programming to prune space and eventually we'll reach a solution where given
当前的设备网格和给定的神经网络，我们找出一个解决方案。
the current device mash and given this neural network, we figure out one solution
这个方案最接近最优解，也就是所有阶段都相等的时候。
that is closest to the optimal, that is when all the stages are equal.
好的，这个问题基本上是可以解决的。这就是我的观点，好吗？
Okay this one is basically solvable. That's my point, okay?
是的，这就是我们基本上解决这个中断路径的方法。
Yeah, this is how we basically solve the um this basically interrupt path.
就像我说的，这个问题可以用动态规划算法来解决。
And like I said, this problem can be solved using dynamic programming algorithm.
在这个动态规划算法中，我们都假设我们知道分配给
And in this um DP algorithm, we all assume that we know the optimal latency of asking
阶段EI在其分配的网格I上的最优延迟。我为什么要强调这一点？
stage EI on its assigned math I. Why I emphasize this?
因为当你尝试在分配的网格上请求阶段时，你需要知道最优解。
Because when you try to ask the stage on assign mesh, you need to know the optimal.
那为什么这里会有最优解呢？
So why there's the optimal here?
因为当你试图把一个阶段分配给一个网格时，对吧，这个网格也有多个设备。
Because when you try to assign a stage to a mesh, right, the mash also have multiple devices.
在我们的优化中，我们假设会在此基础上应用内部对比。
And in our optimization, we assume that we are going to apply intraperism on top of that.
有很多种方法可以选择你想要尝试的内部操作对比方式。
And there are many possible ways for you to choose which intra oper parison you try
用于这个阶段和匹配点，好吗？
to apply for this stage and math pier, okay?
我们想知道这里的最优解。
And we want to know the optimal here.
这就是为什么这是一个分层优化。
That's why, this is a hierarchic opmentation.
所以在外部优化循环中，我们假设我们知道最优解。
So in the outer optimization loop, we assume we know the optimal solution
就像在内部循环中一样，好吗。
in like internal loop, okay.
所以，基本上，我会在这里做个标记。
So So basically, here, I'll notate it here.
基本上，我们假设我们知道最佳解，也就是最佳的内部操作问题解。
So basically, we assume we know the best solution, the best intraop problem solution
针对这个阶段的匹配点，好吗？
for this stage at match pier, okay?
如果我们知道这一点，那么我们基本上可以将这个最优解代入
And if we know that, then we can basically substitute this optimal solution into
那个方程，然后我们用我们的DP算法来求解最优路径的解，对吧？
that equation and we use our DP algorithm to solve for the optimal path like a solution, okay?
有什么问题吗？好。那么问题就是我们到底怎么才能得到那个最优解，对吧？
Any question? Okay. So then the problem is how we can exactly get that optimal, right?
这就是当我们选择阶段划分的时候，选择把神经网络
So that is when we choose stage partison choose to split the neural network
划分成这些阶段，以及当我们选择把集群划分成
into these stages and when we choose to split the cluster into
这些匹配项，以及当我们进行配对时，我们怎么知道
these matches and when we make the pairing, how we know exactly what is
每一对、每个阶段的匹配对的最优解到底是什么。
the optimal solution for each pair, each of the stages matched pair.
好吗？这基本上就引导我们去解决第二个内部优化问题。
Okay? That basically leads us to solve a second internal optimization problem.
那就是我们到底怎么才能准确知道像这样的问题，对吧？
That is how we exactly know like this, right?
问题是我们有一个阶段，我们有一个选择的匹配。我们正在枚举，对吧？
The problem is that we have a stage and we have a choosing match. We are enumerating, right?
好的。鉴于这个阶段和这些枚举的数学内容，我们想要找出
Okay. And given this stage and this enumerated math, we want to figure out what is
执行它的最优方式，也就是最好的intraop解决方案。
the optimal way of executing it with the best intraop solution.
明白吗？这又是一个分层的问题，所以我们需要解决。那么该怎么解决呢？
Okay? And this is another layer of ing, so we need to solve. So how do you solve this?
我想我提到过，基本上，为了解决这个问题，我们实际上是在最小化
I think I mentioned, basically, in order to solve this one, we are basically minimizing
这个阶段在这个mesh上的急性延迟。
the acuten latency of this stage on this mesh.
屏幕延迟由两部分决定。
Thecreen latency is determined by two things.
一是节点成本。
One is the node cost.
第二是边的成本。
The second is the edge cost.
节点成本指的是当你选择某种特定的分区策略时，你会产生一定的成本。
So the node cost constitute of when you choose a particular say partner strategy, you suffer a cost.
边的成本则是在有两个操作符分别选择了不同的分区策略时产生的。
And the edge cost is when you have two operators that are choosing two different parting strategies.
他们需要重新共享，这种重新共享基本上是某种连接性的通信，
They need to reshared that reshared basically constituted of some connective communication,
而这是有代价的。
and that is a cost.
那么我们该怎么做呢？我们可以把这种代价写下来，并尝试最小化这个代价，
So what do we do is we can write down this kind of cost and we try to minimize that cost,
并且我们会试着找出是否能解决这个优化问题。
and we'll try to figure out if we can solve that opmentation.
好吗？让我给你举个例子。
Okay? Let me give you an example.
在这里，假设我用这个符号表示，
So here, suppose I use this notation,
我想你现在应该很熟悉这个了。
I think you are very familiar with this now.
我们来看一个简单的数据流图，其中有一个单独的备忘录，好吗？
And let's just look at a little dataflow graph where a single memo, okay?
就像我说的，这个备忘录基本上就是这个，呃，求和，对吧，
And like I said, this memo is basically this, um, uh, summation, right,
这个循环。对，这其实就是一个循环。
this loop. Okay. It's really a loop.
好的。那么我们可以做的是，枚举所有可能的中断部分策略来处理这个mammo。
Okay. So what do we do is we can enumerate all possible interrup part strategies for this mammo.
好吗？然后我们基本上可以枚举与我们为其选择的部分策略对应的成本。
Okay? And we can basically enumerate the cost, corresponding to the part strategy we choose for it.
好吗？比如说，如果我们选择使用算法一，在循环I中进行划分，对吧？
Okay? So say, if we choose to use algorithm one, where we try to part in loop I, right?
那么如果我们在循环I中划分，第一个矩阵X就是按行划分的，对吧？
So if we part in loop I, then the first matrix X is row partin, okay?
就像我在上次课上提到的，第二个矩阵是复制的，对吧？
And like I mentioned in my last lake, second matrix is replicated, right?
好的，结果就是这样。
Okay. And the result is this.
那么成本是多少？没有成本，对吧？
So what is the cost? No cost, right?
至少没有通信成本。
So there are no communicating costs, at least.
好的，我们还可以选择枚举第二种可能性，
Okay. And we can also choose to enumerate a second possibility that is we
就是我们可以选择算法二，在循环J中进行划分。
can select algorithm to where we parti in Lop J.
所以你基本上得到了这个解法。
So you basically get this solution.
好的，列划分。
Okay, column partition.
或者有时候你可能更喜欢第三种算法，算法三，所以你得到了这个。
Or sometimes you probably prefer a third algorithm, algorithm three, so you get this one.
明白了吗？这就是你选择的。
Okay? And this is what you choose.
还有更多，对吧？在我之前的讲座中
And there are more, right? In my previous lecture
我说过有一些部分铺设的这种情况，好吧，更复杂的那些。
I said there are some partially tiled this kind of thing, okay, more complicated ones.
好的。通过枚举所选择的，嗯，pm算法，你基本上
Okay. And by enumeraating the the chosen, um, pm algorithm, you basically
可以将每个算法与一个代价关联起来。
can associate each algorithm with a cost.
好的，我们简单一点。
Okay. Let's make it simple.
假设第一个算法的代价是1，第二个算法的代价是2，对吧？
Suppose the first algorithm has a cost one, the second algorithm has a cost two, right?
第三个的代价是三。
The third has a cost three.
好的。在这里，代价不仅包括通信，还包括计算，因为当你
Okay. And here, cost includes not only communication but also compute because when you
用不同的方式拆分操作时，计算时间也会有些不同。
split the operating in different ways, the computational time will be slightly different.
好的，好的。但无论如何，我们还是把它们记作代价一、二、三，好吗？
Okay. Okay. But anyway, let's note it as cost one, two, three, okay?
这基本上就像我们在选择拆分算法时，
And then this is basically like when we try to choose a split algorithm,
我们会有一个代价，我们会承受这个代价。
we get a cost, we suffer a cost.
明白了吗？那我们再拓展一下，好吗？
Okay? Then let's extend a little bit, okay.
现在我们有一个稍微复杂一点的神经网络，有两个模块。
And now we have a slightly more complicated neural network we have two metmo.
所以我也把刚才讲的三种算法
So I also put the three algorithms,
放在面板上，这样你们还能记得住。
I just explained on the panel so you know, you still remember it.
那我们要做的就是稍微泛化一下，对吧。
So what do we do is we are going to generise a little bit, right.
我们要从一个备忘录推广到许多许多备忘录。
We are going to generalize from one metmo to many many memos.
所以我要做的是枚举所有的可能性。
So what I do is I'm going to enumerate all possibilities.
我会为每一个备忘录枚举算法，看看会发生什么。
I'm going to enumerate algorithm for each matmo I will see what happens.
在这种情况下，比如说有两个备忘录，它们会被连接在一起，
In this case, say, how two memos, they are going to be connected together,
并且它们会被并行处理。
and they're going to be paralyzed.
所以我做的基本上是先枚举，我先尝试我的第一个选择，好吗？
So what I do is basically I enumerate I first try my first choice, okay?
我为第一个备忘录选择算法一，同时为第二个备忘录也选择算法一。
I choose algorithm one for my first memo and also algorithm one for my second memo.
好吗？然后我就看会发生什么。
Okay? And then I say, what happened?
结果基本上是我发现它们的分区都是低分区。
So what happened is basically I find that their partison are all low parison.
所以如果我把它们连接在一起，没问题。
So if I connect them together, no problem.
没有任何成本，对吧？
There's no cost, right?
是的，我发现就是这样。没有布局转换，也不需要重新加载，没问题。
Yeah, that's what I found. There's no layout conversion, no recharging, okay.
因此，成本为零。
Therefore, the cost is zero.
我可以直接进入竞赛，没有任何问题，对吧？
I can just proceed to competition without any problem, okay?
同样地，我继续枚举，好吗？
And similarly, I continue enumeration, okay?
我尝试为我的第一个备忘录选择算法三，为第二个备忘录选择算法二，好吗？
I try to choose algorithm three for my first memo and algorithm two for my second memo, okay?
如果我这样做，我发现那个分片和那个分片，并不是全部都是绿色的。
And if I do this, I find that that sharding and that sharding, they are not all green.
所以有布局转换，对吧？
So there's a layout conversion, right?
而这种布局转换基本上是，
And this layout of conversing is basically,
我必须把部分和转换成复制，对吧？
I have to convert from um, partial sum into replicate it, okay?
这会有一定的代价，对吗？
And this has a cost, right?
我把这个过程重复了很多很多次，对吧？这些都被简化了。
I repeated this for many, many, many times, okay? This is all reduced.
好的，我承受了或者说降低了成本。
Okay. I suffer or reduced cost.
我会一直这样做，好吗？
I keep doing this, okay?
我会不断枚举所有的可能性。
I keep enumerating all the possibilities.
我已经告诉你了，这是有限空间。你可以这么做。
I already told you this is the filane space. You can do that.
你也可以为此写一个算法，对吧？
And you can write algorithm to that, okay?
我会一直这么做，
And I keep doing this,
我基本上就是枚举所有的可能性。
I basically enumerate all the possibility.
比如说，在这个例子中，
For example, in this case,
我选择了算法一和算法二，并且我知道代价将会是全收集（all gather）。
I choose algorithm one and algorithm two, and I know that the cost is going to be all gather.
现在，你明白这个问题了吧？
Now, you understand the problem, right?
所以我做的事情是，我试图为intraparism找出最优解，
So what I do what I try to figure out the optimal solution for intraparism is
因为我会生成所有的可能性，然后计算代价，并把它们加在一起。
because I generate all the possibilities and I count cost, and I add them together.
然后我尝试找出能让代价方程最小化的那个方案。
Then I try to figure out the one that minimize the cost equation.
好吗？很好。就像我说的，这是代价矩阵，如果你在不同的分区之间切换，
Okay? Good. Cool. Like I said, this is the cost matrix, if you swap between
你会付出一定的代价，这就是那个代价。
different partien you suffer a cost and this is the cost.
好的。如果我对整个数据流图都这样做，
Okay. And if I do this for my entire data flow graph,
我基本上可以写出类似这样的东西。
I can basically write down, um, something like this.
当我拆分算子时，我的计算会发生变化，对吗？
When I split the operator, my computation changes, right?
所以我知道这会有一些代价。
So I know there is some cost.
当我为不同的节点选择不同的拆分策略时，
And when I choose different split strategy for different nodes,
我知道有可能需要重新共享，这种重新共享基本上
I know they are going to there's a chance that maybe we need a reshting that resharing basically
就对应了通信和连接，对吧？
corresponds to, communication, connective, right?
我也知道存在一条边的代价。
And I know there's a edge cost.
所以基本上我的目标是尽量最小化节点代价加上边的代价。
So basically my goal is trying to minimize the node cost plus edge cost.
当然，我还需要考虑内存，比如峰值内存这样的约束。
Of course, I need to subject my memory, like a peak memory kind of like a constraint.
明白吗？如果你对此稍微有些了解的话，
Okay? And if you are slightly familiar with this,
这个问题其实也可以用解析解来解决，
and this can also be solved using an analytical solution,
这是IOP问题，整数线性规划。
this is the IOP problem, integer linear program.
明白了吗？所以你可以不断枚举keeper，并且可以使用现有的IOP软件来解决它，
Okay? So you keep enumerating keeper and you can use the existing IOP software to solve it,
它会给你最优解。
and it will give you the optimal solution.
好的，酷。这基本上就是Opa的整体情况。
Okay, cool. That is basically a global picture of Opa.
那么总结一下。
So just a recap.
好的。我有一个上层，我把新的tw分成几个阶段。
Okay. I have a upper layer, which I split the new tw into stages.
我将每个阶段与从集群中选择的子匹配进行匹配。
I match each stage to also selected submatch from the cluster.
在内部循环中，
And in the internal loop,
我有一个非常好的IOP公式，我在枚举合作方策略，
I have this very nice IOP formulation where I enumerating the partner strategy
对每个操作符我都会计算成本。
for each operator I count cost.
所以我的口头目标是尽量减少这种两级增强。明白吗？好的。
So my oral goal is I try to minimize this two level augmentation. Okay? Cool.
但如果我把这些都放在一起，这个问题就会变得
But if I put all this together, then this problem becomes uh
无法解决，因为它太复杂了。
insolvable because it's too complicated.
好的，明白。
Yeah, cool.
实际上，当我们做这个opera工作时，在2022年非常受欢迎。
Okay. And indeed, when we do this opera work, it was very popular in 2022.
我们取得了相当不错的表现。
We get a pretty good performance.
当我们尝试选择新工作并运行
When we try to put when we try to select new work and we run
这个opera，来找出这种性能策略时，我们发现，在很多很多情况下，
this opera and to figure out this performance strategy, we find that in many, many cases,
它确实能找到比人工设计更好的策略。
it can indeed find a strategy that's better than human design.
好的，明白。回到我的论点。
Okay, yeah. Okay, back to my argument.
首先，我想告诉你一个事实，Opa 并没有流行起来。
So first, I want to tell you a fact Opa didn't take off.
是的，我用那篇论文找到了教职工作，但它并没有流行起来。
Yeah, I use that paper to get a faculty job, but that doesn't take off.
所以你知道原因，对吧？因为 Opa 是一种自动排列方法。
So any reason You know argument, right, because Opa is automatic perdition method.
那这种方法什么时候会大放异彩呢？就是当我们有很多新的网络架构时。
So when will this kind of method shine, we have a lot of new network architectures,
因为关键的价值在于我可以减少开发者花在排列策略上的时间。
Because the key value purpose is that I can reduce the developer's time
去琢磨排列策略。
to figure out the perm srategy.
但实际上，论文发表后，模型已经收敛了。
But what happens is after I publish this paper, the model is converging.
现在只有一种模型，就是 transformer。
There's only one model, transformers.
是的，所以大家并没有用这个方法。
Yeah, so people don't use this.
他们只是用专家设计的方法，因为现在只有一种策略。
Yeah. They just use like expert design because there's only one strategy for it.
好的，酷。我希望这样说得清楚。
Okay. Cool. I hope that makes sense.
有什么问题吗？嗯，嗯，这比我的好。
Any question? Yeah. Yeah, it's better than mine.
嗯，这基本上就是03。
Yeah. It's basically the 03.
03最后覆盖。
03 cover last.
好的，酷。你可以看到这是一个非常好的公式。是的。
Okay. Cool. Yeah, you can see this is a very nice formulation. Yeah.
嗯，请说。
Yeah, please.
是的，但是不同公司之间的数据差异太小了，这样就失去了
Yeah, but the data between different companies is so small that it defeats
这种编译器的意义。
the purpose of this kind of compiler.
嗯，好的，酷。
Yeah. Yeah. Okay, cool.
是的，选择你要解决的问题。
Yeah, choose the problem to walk on.
你需要让quidty预测未来。
You need to have the quidty predict the future.
好的。那么总结一下，在这个palism空间里，好吗？
Yeah. Okay. So to summarize, in this palism space, okay?
我想我介绍了两大类prism，intra op和interrupt。
I think I introduced two major classes of prisms, intra op and interrupt.
我还介绍了围绕它构建的许多系统产物。
I also introduced a lot of system artifacts build around it.
基本上我画了三个圈，
It basically I draw three circles,
inter我也讲了自动化方法。
Inter and also I covered automatic approaches.
基本上，megatR、Mc tensor flow和GHR，这三个属于Intraop，因为它们
Basically, megatR Mc tensor flow and GHR, these three belong to Intraop because they
基本上都是在处理tensor和expert partism。
basically are playing with tensor and expert partism.
很明显，MctGHR已经发展起来了，因为Microtron是每天都在用的TP。
And apparently MctGHR they already taken off, because Microtron is a TP that use every day.
DHR，他们提出了一种EP expert parison，已经在MOE中使用了。
DHR, they propose a EP expert parison that has been used in MOE.
好吗？我说过，
Okay? And I said,
GCR基本上是Msenerflow新版本的延续，
GCR is basically a continuation of new version
所以你可以把它们当作同一个项目，好吗？还有w two，
of Msenerflow so you can think of them as a same project, okay and there's a w two,
GPi、Pip dream和Dipo。
GPi, Pip dream and Dipo.
我没有讲Dipo，但GPiP失败了，对吧？为什么？
I didn't cover Dipo, but GPiP it failed, right? Why?
因为它有一个缺点，就是内存问题。
Because it has a drawback, the memory.
对。好。WY FMB基本上是实现
Right. Okay. I WY FMB is basically the one that implementing
MctroniT的那个项目，而且那个项目也起飞了。
MctroniT and that project also take off.
好吗？还有Pip dream，就像我说的，它在网络上有问题，因为它是
Okay? And Pip dream, like I said, it has a problem on your networks because it's
一个异步流水线并行方式，这会影响收敛性。
a synchronous pipeline parism and it affects the convergence.
所以这个项目没有起飞。
So this project doesn't take off.
好吗？而且还有一些自动化系统。好吗？
Okay? And there are also some automatic systems. Okay?
关于flex flow，我也没讲到，但它们是更早期的工作。
To flex flow, I didn't cover this too, but they are earlier works.
基本上就是01、02、03，显然03和02起飞了，对吧？
And is basically 01, two, three, and apparently 03 and 02 take off, right?
因为它太简单了，是的。
Because it's so simple, yeah.
还有另一个共定位错误，就是斯坦福教职工那个。
And there's another colocal error, the Stanford faculty one.
而这个项目很遗憾没有起飞，因为它需要太多算力。
And this one didn't take off, unfortunately, because it requires so many compute.
只有谷歌能做到。是的。还有，我的Alpha项目也没有起飞。好的，酷。
Only Google can do that. Yeah. And also, there's my work Alpha didn't take off. Okay. Cool.
但它处于中间地带。嗯，好的，酷。
But it's in the middle. Yeah. Okay, um, cool.
这基本上就是这个领域的空间了。
That's pretty much, the space in parism.
所以鉴于现在的情况，就像我说的，目前大多数模型都是transformer结构，
So given that, like I said, given today that models are mostly transformers,
我今天讲的内容基本上就是训练模型时用到的方法。
I would say what I taught today is basically the one that is used in training models.
我认为现在很少有人在这个领域发明新的数据了，
I would say there are very few data that people are inventing on
因为模型本身已经不再发生大的变化了。
in the area because model is not changing anymore.
但也许有一天，比如一两年后，当大家对新模型有了更深入的研究，
But maybe someday, like in one or two years when people study, uh better on new models,
可能我们还需要重新回顾这个问题，好吗？
probably we will need to revisit this again, okay?
哦。那我想花大概10分钟时间，给大家带来一个非常非常实用的分享，
Oh. Okay, then I want to spend probably 10 minutes to give you a very very practical guest,
这很特别，因为全世界其他地方你都得不到这10分钟的内容，
this is very special because nowhere else in the world, you can get this 10 minutes,
因为这是基于我五年来不断调优的经验总结。
because this is based on my five years of tuning this.
我一直都是亲自动手在做这些工作的。
I've been working this, you know, hands on fashion.
我这几天一直在调试，你知道的，做这种工作的时候就是这样。
I have been tuning this days and nights, you know, when I do this kind of work.
嗯，我可以把我的经验教给你。
Yeah. I can give you my lesson.
好的。如果你开始在这个领域工作，用pism训练你的神经网络，
Okay. And if you start working in this area, if you start training your neur networks using pism,
你可能会发现这页幻灯片非常有用。
you'll probably find this slide pretty useful.
那么一般来说，你怎么选择prism呢？
So in general, how do you choose prism?
大致来说，如果你的模型不是transformer，
So so big picture wise, you can if your model is not transformer,
你基本上可以用这些编译器。
okay, you basically can use these compilers.
就像我说的，这就是编译器的价值所在，对吧，B，好的。
Like I said, because that's where compiler values come, right, B okay.
但如果你的模型完全是基于transformer的，其实有一些设计特征。
But if your model is purely transformer based, okay, essentially, there's some like design traits.
你可以手动按照这些设计特征来搜索，明白吗？
Okay, and you can basically manually, search following this design traits, okay?
有几个因素需要考虑。
Uh there are a few factors to consider.
一个是你有多少个GPU，对吧？
One is, how many GP you have, right?
因为如果你的集群小和集群大，决策是不同的。
Because if you have a small and if you have a large cluster, the decisions are different.
第二个是你的模型大小。
Second is your model size.
如果你是小模型，就不需要切分。
You have a small model, you don't need pism.
大模型，你就需要大量切分。
Large model, you need a lot of partism.
然后是JCT，也就是作业完成时间，看你能否在规定时间内完成作业，
Then JCT, job completing time, whether you can finish your job in given time,
还有通信带宽，你有多少带宽等等。
and also communicating bandwidth, how many bandos you have, et cetera.
明白了吗？现在我来快速讲一下这个过程。
Okay? Now, I'm going to run through this.
我希望你能理解每一个决策点。
I want you to understand every decision point.
如果你不明白，随时可以来我的办公室，因为我觉得这其实是整个PISM部分的精华幻灯片。
If you don't understand, feel free to come to my office because I think this is actually,
呃，这是整个PISM部分的精炼总结。
uh the distilled slide for the entire pism part.
好的。你首先要问的问题是，你的模型能否放进一张GPU里。
Okay. You start with asking the question, if your model can fit into a single GPU.
当然，你要从这个问题开始。明白吗？
Of course, you start with this question. Okay?
如果可以，那你很幸运。
And yes, you're lucky.
你在训练一个小模型。
You're training a small model.
好的，然后你会开始问我的JCT是否可以，对吧？
Okay. And you start asking if my JCT is okay, right?
也就是说，我能否在规定时间内完成训练，对吗？
So if I can finish my training in given time, okay?
如果可以，那你就没问题了。
And if yes, then you are good.
好的，你就没有任何压力了？
Okay. You don't have any pressure?
嗯，但如果不是这样，你之所以这么做，是因为你的模型可以放进一块GPU，对吧？
Um, but if not, what you do is because your model can fit into a single GPU, right?
所以你不想让你的系统变得复杂。
So you don't want to complicate your system.
所以你开始使用数据并行，对吧？
So you start skinning data parism, right?
因为一旦你开始用数据并行，你就可以加速你的任务，
Because once you start scanning with data parism, you can accelerate your job and you
并且可以保持在JCT的范围内，明白吗？
can stay within JCT, okay?
所以你基本上是通过增加更多的GPU和更多的数据并行来扩展，
So you basically skill with more GPUs and by adding more data parism you basically
这样你就可以保持在JCO GCT的范围内，没问题。
stay within JCO GCT is okay.
明白了吗？然后，当然，你会有这个分支，对吧？
Okay? And then, of course, you're going to have this branch, right?
现实情况是，我的很多模型都无法放进一块GPU。
And this is the reality. My many models cannot fit into a single GPU.
明白吗？我觉得在这一点上，你可能已经知道，首先还是……
Okay? I think at this point, you probably know the first thing is still,
你应该避免让你的系统变得复杂。
you should avoid complicating your system.
每当你开始做分布式系统时，你的代码就会变得非常复杂。
Whenever you start doing distributing system, your code is going to be very complicated.
所以你要从简单的东西开始。
So you want to start with something simple.
你要问问自己能不能用我在上一节课讲过的内存导向方法。
You ask yourself if you can use the memory orientation I taught in my previous lecture.
基本上我还是会尝试应用一些内存导向，并试着把我的模型塞进一个Gib里。
I basically still try to apply some memory orenation and try to fit my model into a single Gib.
我想在我的内存导向讲座里，
I think in my memory orienting lecture,
我也有一个演示。
I also have a ditera.
你可以去那里再看一遍，好吗？
You can go there and look at it again, okay?
所以是的，你其实可以尝试做检查点重物化，或者类似的这种方法，
So yes, you can actually play a checkpoint rematerialization, or this kind of, uh,
还记得微批处理吧？
still remember micro Batching, right?
是的。梯度累积其实是一种让你的模型适配的方法，然后你要问自己你的J是否合适。
Yeah. Grad accumulation is kind of trick to fit your model, then you ask yourself if your J is okay.
合适吗？如果是的话，那你就没问题。
Okay? And if yes, then you are still good.
你不需要分布式系统，明白吗？
You don't need to distribute systems, okay?
当然，下一步就是不行。
Of course, the next one is no.
明白吗？所以当你枚举所有可能的内存组织方式时，
Okay? So either when you enumerate all the possible memory organizations,
包括远程化，还有梯度累积，通常我们不会用交换，因为就像我说的，
including remotenization, and also green accumulation, usually we don't do swap because like I said,
交换基本上会让你的GCT变慢，对吧。
swap is basically we are going to slow down your GCT, right.
所以基本上，你可以尝试检查点远程化和梯度累积，如果你还是
So basically, you try checkpoint remotization and, uh, green accumulation, and if you still
不能适配，或者你的CT基本上不合适。
cannot fit or your CT is basically not okay.
你就可以开始考虑使用多进程并行，明白吗？
You start considering using piss multiparisms, okay?
你开始考虑在这个阶段引入内部或互操作性，
You start considering incorporating intra or interoperism, um, at this point,
你首先应该关闭之前关于内存组织的探索。
you should first turn off your previous exploration that is memory organization y.
因为大多数内存组织会把计算和内存混在一起处理，你不希望这样做。
Because most memory organization will treat compute for memory, you don't want to do that.
现在，你已经决定进行扩展，所以你有充足的内存。
Now, you have decided to scale out, so you have plenty of memory.
所以你不想把计算性能浪费掉。
So you don't want to treat treat flops.
好的，然后在这个阶段，一旦你开始决定，
Okay. And then at this point you once you start deciding,
好的，我要用多处理器了，我该怎么做？
okay, I'm going to use Multipis what do I do?
我开始查看我的集群，我有多少带宽。
I start looking at my cluster, how many bandos I have.
好吧，基本上有两个分支。
Okay? So basically, there are two branches.
一个是，我有一个集群，其中
One is, I have a cluster where
所有GPU都通过mink连接在一起。
GPUs are all connected with mink.
比如说，我只有GPU，而且这些GPU都在同一个节点里。
For example, I only have GPUs, and these GPUs are inside one node.
好的，另一种情况基本上是你根本没有任何意义。
Okay. Another case is basically either you don't have a meaning at all.
比如说，你是中国公司，对吧？
For example, you are your Chinese firm, okay?
或者，你就是没有任何意义，对吧？
Or, you just don't have a meaning, yeah, okay?
我们先来看左边这部分，好吗？
Let's go to the left part first, okay?
是的，我做的事情是有意义的。
Yes, I have a meaning what I do.
如果你有a，你可以做任何你想做的事情。
If you have a, you can do whatever you want.
就像我说的，你基本上可以无限绑定。
Like I said, you bind basically infinite.
是的，通信非常少，对吧？
Yeah. Communication is very minimal, okay?
所以你可以选择任何一种并行方式，但通常是TP tenerpis，就像我刚才说的，
So you do whatever kind of pim you want, but typically it's TP tenerpis because like I said,
ton其实很简单，对吧？
ton is pretty easy, right?
只需要一个单一的算子。对。
Just a single ore. Yeah.
你在作业里试试看，好吗？
You do that in your homework, okay?
但是如果我用tinder部分，还是放不下，对吗？
But if I apply tinder part I still cannot fit, right?
因为我的模型太大了，对吧？那我该怎么办？
Because my model is so large, Okay? What do I do?
有两种方法，一种是你开始开启内存优化。
So two ways, one you start turning on memory ogenation.
你开始开启检查点，开始开启梯度累积，
You start turning on checkpointing, you start turning on green accumulation,
你减小你的批量大小，看看能不能行。
you reduce your byside effective biside and say if it works.
第二种方法，当然就是你需要更多的GPU。
The second way, of course, you need more GPU,
GPU 不够用，所以你需要扩展你的技能，超越GPU，对吧？
GPU is not enough, so you skill you skill beyond GPUs, okay?
所以无论如何，最终你都会遇到需要扩展GPU的情况，对吧？
So either way, eventually you will converge to a point where you need to skill out GPUs, okay?
如果你扩展GPU，你就会面临第二个分支，也就是你拥有的GPU是
And if you skill GPS, you are facing the second branch, which is you have GPUs that are
通过非高带宽互连连接的，这些互连的带宽远低于高带宽互连，对吧？
connected using non wilink interconnects, which are Iternet much lower bandwidth than wilink. Okay?
那你该怎么办呢？当然，我们需要根据可用带宽来讨论。
What do you do? Okay? Of course, we need to discuss based on the available bandwidth.
所以有很多很多不同的网络技术。
So there are many many different networking technologies.
所以有两个分支，对吧。
So two branches, okay.
如果你是一家非常有钱的公司，你很开放，你就像这种大型企业，
If you are a very rich company, you are open air, you are like this kind of a big firm,
比如说像“XI”，那你可能就在那个拥有高带宽连接的分支，对吧？
XI, then you probably in that branch that you have high bandwidth connect, okay?
也许不是最高带宽，但也非常接近了，对吧？
Maybe not unwink but pretty close, okay?
比如每个GPU的带宽是100 GBPS。
Like 100 GBPS per GPU bandwidth.
但是wilink是每GB 400 GPS。
But wilink is 400 GPS per GB.
是的，你只是那里的第一个。
Yeah, you are only one first of that.
没关系。但如果你不是一家富有的公司，你很可能就在那个分支。
It's fine. But if you are not a rich firm, you're probably in that branch.
所以你的带宽非常低，比如说25。
So you have a very low bandwidth. For example, 25.
如果你试图从AWS租用一些DPs，你也会在那个分支。
If you hire if you basically try to rent some DPs from AWS, you are in that branch.
好的，好的。我们来谈谈第一个分支。
Okay. Okay. Let's talk about the first branch.
所以在第一个分支，如果你有很多带宽，我们有，你基本上会尝试扩展，
So in the first branch, if you have a lot of bandwidth we do, you basically try to skill out,
你需要O2，对吧？
you need 02, right?
因为在O2中，如果你还记得，通信成本是一次或减少，对吧？
Because in 02, if you remember, the communicating cost is one or reduce, right?
好的。02和03相比，问题在于它不共享权重。
Okay. And 02 has compared to 03, the problem is, it doesn't share weights.
记住，代价是16，对不起，是14加40除以N再加2，对吧？
Remember, the cost is 16, sorry, it's 14 plus 40 divided by N plus two, right?
那就是02。你从02开始，原因是
That's 02. Okay. You start with 02, and the reason you start with
你选择02是因为通信量更少。
02 because you have less communication.
你只需要做一次reduce操作。
You just have one single reduce.
但缺点是你会浪费更多内存，因为你没有共享权重。
But the drawback is you waste a little bit more memory because you don't share weights.
明白吗？但如果你还是无法装下你的模型，
Okay? But if you still cannot fit your model,
02的话，你基本上就要升级到03，对吧？
02, what do you basically upgrade to 03, right?
所以在03中，你的峰值内存会进一步减少，因为两部分也共享了，对吧？
So I 03, your peak memory is further reduced because the two was also shared, right?
但你还会多一次0.5的reduce操作。
But you suffer another 0.5 reduce.
你正在支付1.5倍的通信成本降低费用。
You are paying a 1.5 reduce communicating cost.
好的。但就像我说的，因为你的GP噪声很大，所以全部归约也没问题。
Okay. But like I said, because your GP has high noise, so all reduce is okay.
是的，是的，你开始探索03吧。
Yeah. Yeah, you start exploring 03.
好的，你还是无法适配，或者它无法适配。
Okay, you still cannot fit or it do.
好的，当然，你要开启内存累积功能。
Okay. Of course, you turn on memory cumation.
你会开始做检查点，开始做各种绿色累积操作。
You'll start doing checkpoint, you start doing all this kind of green accumulation
直到你能适配为止。如果还是无法适配。
until you can fit. Still cannot fit.
好吗？你会怎么做？你可以直接修正，没问题。
Okay? What do you do? You can just correct, okay.
嗯，那是个玩笑。
Um, that's a joke.
只要不断增加倍数，直到你能适配为止。
Just add multiples until you can fit.
好吗？对，只要多花点钱就行了，好吗？
Okay? Yeah, just pay more money. Okay?
这样说有道理吗？好的，没问题。
Does that make sense? Okay, cool.
但当然，我们首先要尽量减少GPU的使用，因为那是我们自己的钱，对吧？
But of course, we want to first minimize number of GP use because that was our money, right?
但如果你还是无法把所有这些可能性都枚举出来，还是无法满足要求，
But if you cannot, basically enumera all these possibilities you still cannot fit,
你应该向你的经理申请更多资源，明白吗？
you should ask multiples from your manager, okay?
那么，我们来探索一个品牌，好吗？
Uh, then let's explore a brand, okay?
现在，你没有这种节点间GPU的高带宽。
Now, you don't have this kind of high banistween GPUs across nodes.
你只有大约每个GPU 25GB/s的低带宽。
You only have low band Wis for about 25 GPS per GP.
就像我说的，在这种情况下，你就要开始做互操作性了。
Like I said, in this case, you start doing interoperatism.
你要开始引入流水线机制。为什么呢？
You start introducing pipeline Pism. Why?
就像我说的，流水线并行只在边界之间传递残差。
Because like I said, pipeline parism only communicate sent residual between boundaries.
所以通信量非常小。
So it's very little communication.
你不会被大幅度拖慢，好吗？
You are not going to be slowed down a lot, okay?
好的。一旦你开始考虑跨分区并行，
Okay. Once you start considering interpartism,
你基本上就引入了另一层复杂性。
you are basically introduced another layer of complexity.
也就是说你必须调整你的微批次数，以最小化你的空泡，对吧？
That is you have to tune your lumber micro baatches right to minimize your bubble, right?
但是如果你像你说的那样增加微批次数，
But if you increase your number of mini batches, like that you point out,
你会降低你的算术强度。
you are going to reduce your arismt intensity.
所以你需要在空泡数量和每个算子的AI之间取得平衡。
So you want to strike a balance between the lumber bubbles and the AI on each operator.
这基本上又创造了一个决策空间。
So that basically creates another like decision space.
你需要非常努力地调整，才能找到好的配置，明白吗？
You have to tune very hard to figure out good configuration, okay?
所以要调整microbatch和micro batch的大小。
So tune microbatchy and the micro baades size.
明白吗？你要一直这样做，直到你能适配为止。
Okay? And you keep doing this until you can fit.
如果还是适配不了，就加倍，好吗？没有其他办法了。
If you cannot fit, just add multiples, okay? No more are the solution.
好的。当然，也有例外，就是你是Tip Sik。
Okay. And, of course, there's exception that is you are Tip Sik.
在Deep six的情况下，你没有wilink，明白吗？
So in Deep six's case, you don't have wilink, okay?
你只有一种类似妥协版的link，是美国政府批准的那种。
You only have a kind of like a compromise version of link, right by the US government.
你还会遇到dips之间的边界问题。
And you also have a little bit like boundaries between dips.
那你该怎么办？我们后面会讲这个，好吗？
So what do you do? We are going to cover this later, okay?
好的。明白了吗？
Yeah. Cool. Does that make sense?
好的，我希望你能理解DC的要点，好吗？
Okay, I want you to understand DC in point, okay?
所以基本上，如果你现在在做transformer，做AM，你就要按照这个流程图来。
So this is basically today if you are doing transformer, you are doing AM, you follow this dalgram.
好的，明白了。
Okay. Yeah.
关于带连接，你需要把每个GPU都互相连接吗？这个是怎么实现的？
For the bed connect, do you need to connect each GPU each other GPO how does that?
我看不到所有的配置，但我可以给你IBS的配置。
I cannot see all the configures but I can give you the config in IBS.
基本上，IBS会为每个GPU安装Iranet硬件。
Basically IBS, they are going to install Iranet hardware for each GPU.
举个例子，如果你要租用，
For example, if you are going to rent, say,
比如说，从IBS租用P型服务器，里面有四块A100。
P for instance, from IBS, where you have four a 100.
基本上每个GPU会有一个Iranet，这意味着整个节点有八个Iranet。
Basically EGPU is going to have one Iranet, which means that the entire node has eight Iranets.
好的，明白了，挺好的。
Okay. Yeah. Okay. Cool. Okay.
这是精简版。
This is the distilled version.
我希望你能理解其中的原理，这非常重要。
I hope you understand the rationale behind this, very important.
那我们大概可以把这里的一切收尾了。
Then we can probably wrap up everything here.
我们已经全部讲完了。
We covered everything.
所以通常我们可以结束这门课程了。
So typically we can end this course.
但让我们继续进入RM部分。
But let's move on into RM.
实际上，我们接下来要做的，如果你还没明白的话，
We are going to actually, you're not already understand
就是掌握Mergent系统背后的所有技术，基本上是这样，好吗？
all the techniques behind Mergent systems, mostly, okay?
我们接下来要做的，基本上就是把这些点连起来。
What do we do next is basically connect the dots.
然后我们拿一个模型。这个模型基本上是
And we take a model. That model is basically
RM，我们会尝试重新审视这些技术。
RM and we try to revisit techniques.
那么，为什么我们要为那个RM做出那样的决定呢，好吗？
So why we make that decision for that RM, okay?
很好。那么我们继续进入第三章。
Cool. Okay, let's move on to our third chapter.
在本课程的这一部分，我将会讲解这些内容。
So in this part of this course, I'm going to cover these things.
好的。我首先当然会带你们快速了解一下transformers和attention。
Okay. I'm going to first, of course, give you a very quick go through of transformers and attention.
然后我当然还会，
And then I'm going to of course,
我需要介绍一下斯金定律，因为你们需要理解为什么我们要训练如此庞大的模型，对吧？
I need to introduce skin law because you need to understand why we train such large models, right?
这是因为我们遵循斯金定律，好吗？
It's because we are following skin law, okay?
然后可能下周我们会把这些点串联起来。
And then probably next week we are going to connect the dots.
我们会告诉你们为什么我们要采用这种opium训练方式。
We are going to tell you why we apply this kind of opium training.
我认为你们很快就会弄明白很多事情，好吗？
I think you all figure out a lot of things pretty soon, okay?
其中有一个特别的点就是flash attention，这是一种非常快的注意力内核，
And there's one special thing to that is flash attention, which is a very fast attaching kernel,
我们必须要讲解它们。
and we have to cover them.
然后我们的话题会转到推理服务上。
And then we move on our topic to serving an inference.
在推理服务中，有很多新内容我们之前没有涉及到，
And in serving an inference, there are a lot of new things that we didn't cover,
因为那对IM来说非常特殊。
because that's very special to IM.
最后，我们会把所有内容串联起来，并且用最后一节课
And finally, we are going to connecting the dots, and we are going to use our last lecture
来回顾Deep，我会和你们一起阅读Withy的论文。
to review Deep I'm going to basically read Withy paper with you.
我会分析他们为什么要这么做。
I'm going to reason why they do this.
好吗？我觉得你们会喜欢的，好吗？
Okay? I think you'll be enjoying that, okay?
最后，如果你有时间的话，
And lastly, if you have time,
我会讲一些热门话题。好的。
I'm going to cover hot topics. Okay.
很酷。那么，什么是ARM？
Cool. Okay, so what is ARM?
ARM基本上就是做词元预测，对吧？
So ARM is basically token prediction, right?
我们有一个前缀，然后我们尝试建模概率分布。
So we have a prefix and we try to model the probability distribution.
在给定前缀的条件下，我们预测下一个词。
Conditional prefix we predict next word.
好的，像词元预测那样。
Okay. Lake token prediction.
比如说，我们想要建模这样一个句子。
For example, we want to model the sentence.
圣地亚哥的天气非常好，然后我们尝试输出下一个词元，
San Diego has very nice and we try to output the next token,
对吧？它可能是冲浪、天气或者下雪，但我们会调整我们的概率分布。
right It could be surfing weather or snow, but we are going to align our probability.
同样的事情，旧金山是创新之都还是无家可归之都，对吧？
Same thing, San Francisco is the city of innovation or homess, right?
然后我们要给出一个概率。
And we are going to give a probability.
明白了吗？一旦我们有了这个概率，我们就要从
Okay? And once we have this probability, we are going to sample from
这个单词的概率分布中采样，对吧？这基本上就是RM。
this probability distribution of words, right? That's basically RM.
好的。如果我们写下这个公式，我们基本上知道，比如说u，
Okay. And if we write down the equation, we basically know that u for example,
圣地亚哥有很好的天气的概率。
probability of San Diego has very nice weather.
我们基本上可以把它展开成很多条件概率的乘积，好吗？
We can basically expand it into a lot of, like, a factor idton of conditional probability, okay?
我们从第一个词“圣地亚哥”开始。
We start with the first word San Diego.
这里我把“圣地亚哥”当作一个词，好吗？呃，请跟上。
So here I take San Diego as a single word, okay? Uh, bear me.
然后在“圣地亚哥”这个条件下，下一个词是“有”的概率是多少，
And then conditional on San Diego, we have a probability of next word being has,
然后我们继续这样做，每个城市都更好，对吧？
and then we keep doing so very city and better, okay?
然后我们把它们一起分解，我们就得到了整个序列的概率，对吗？
And we factorism together, we get the probability of this entire sequence, right?
所以如果我们写下数学形式，基本上就是一个，对吧，当我们在这里尝试的时候
So if we write down the mathematical form, is basically a one, right and when we try to so here we
我们试图去建模这个过程，好吗？
try to try to model this, okay?
实际上，如果你想改变这种模型，我们该怎么做？
And in reality, if you want to change this kind of model, what we do?
我们观察了很多这种类型的现象，对吧？
We observe a lot of this kind of symptoms, right?
这些基本上是我们从互联网、人类和书籍中收集到的样本，
And this is basically the copies we connected from Internet from what human in books,
我们观察了很多这样的东西。
we observe a lot of this kind of things.
然后我们尝试用最大似然估计来估算参数，
And we try to use maximum likelihood estimation to basically estimate the primeters,
我们设计模型的方式基本上是我们设计的模型是
the way we design the model is basically we design model that is
能够预测下一个标记，对吧？
capable of predicting the next token, right?
所以这个模型基本上会接收一个前缀，并预测下一个标记出现的概率。
And so this model basically will take a prefix and predict the probability of the next token.
通过按照这个公式将所有这些因素结合起来，
And by factorizing all this together following this equation,
我们基本上得到了这个观测序列的概率，并且我们试图最大化
we basically get a probability of this observed sequence, and we try to maximize
所有观测数据的似然。明白吗？
the likelihood of all observed data. Okay?
这就是典型的机器学习。
This is typical machine learning.
有什么问题吗？没有的话，这还挺好的，对吧？
Any questions on this? No, this is pretty good, right?
那么我们尝试建模这种条件概率的方式，基本上就是
So the way that we try to model this conditional probability is basically
我们使用语言模型，对吧？
we use language model, right?
Transformer。明白了吗？那我们怎么做呢？
Transformers. Okay? So how do we do that?
有很多方法，但尽管有很多方法，本质上还是一个序列预测问题。
There are many ways, but despite many ways, is basically a sequence prediction problem
我们有输入x1、x2、x3、x4，然后我们尝试预测输出。
where we have input x1x2, x3x4, and we try to predict output.
明白了吗？在下一个预测中，这有点不同，因为我们要
Okay? I M in nextcen predicting, this is a little bit different because we are going to
应用因果关系，也就是我们观察到X1。
apply cadal relationship that is we observe X one.
我们尝试预测下一个词。
We try to predict the next word.
好的，我们观察到X1和X2，然后尝试预测下一个词，
Okay, we observe X one and X two, we try to predict the next word,
因为我们是在建模条件。
because we are model the condition.
好的，这就是一个非常典型的序列到序列模型，
Okay. And this is a very typical sequence to sequence model,
有很多方法可以实现，对吧？
and there are many ways to do that, right?
我认为其中一种方法是RNN，但我们知道RNN在这方面表现不好，因为它很难扩展，对吧？
And I think one way is RN, but we know RN is bad on this because it's very hard to scale, right?
就像我们在第一节课中讨论的，ARN有那些隐藏状态，对吧？
Be ARN has those hidden states we talked about in our first lecture, okay?
而今天的方法基本上就是注意力机制。
And today's approach is basically attention.
注意力机制非常擅长做这件事。
Attention is very capable of doing this.
那什么是注意力机制呢？这基本上就是注意力机制。
So what is attention? So this is basically attention.
注意力机制基本上，呃，一般来说指的是
Attention is basically, uh general attention generally refers to
我们将各个状态结合起来的方法。
the approach that we combine individual states.
所以在这里我们观察到这些词，对吧？
So here we observe this kind of words, right?
我们有隐藏状态，比如说有它的表示，比如嵌入向量。
We have hidden we have a representation, for example, embedding for it.
好吗？然后我们会在其上堆叠很多注意力层。
Okay? And we are going to, uh stack a lot of attention layers on top of it.
这里就是其中一层。
And here is one layer.
我们建模的方式是，在每个隐藏状态下，
And the way we model that is we each hidden state at
在隐藏的标记位置，
the token position at the hidden token position to
基本上可以关注所有前一层的状态。
basically attend to all the previous layer states.
我们计算隐藏状态的方法，基本上是尝试做一种加权求和，
And the way we calculate this hidden states, basically we try to take this kind of weighted sum,
这里是前一层的观测值，这是一个权重，我们对它们进行加权求和，
and here is the previous layers observation, and this is a weight, and we weighted some of
然后得到下一层的隐藏状态。
them and we get the next layers of hidden states.
这基本上就是注意力机制，对吧？
This is basically attention, okay?
所以直观上来说，
And so intuitively here,
SI 是一个十乘十的矩阵，用来计算输入中第 i 个位置
SI is a ten square that computes how relevant the position Ice input
与当前隐藏输出的相关性。
is to the current hidden output.
有不同的方法来决定如何计算ten square，
And there are different methods to decide how ten square is being computed,
但出于某种原因，我们把它转换成了自注意力。
but for some reason, we convert it to self attention.
好的。那么在自注意力中，基本上自注意力指的是
Okay. So in self attention, basically self attention refers to
一种特定形式的注意力机制。
a particular form of attention mechanism.
所以在自注意力中，我们有一种特殊的机制来计算
So in self attention, we have a special mechanism to calculate the
注意力分数S。明白了吗？那我们是怎么计算的呢？
atten square S. Okay? So how we calculate that?
我们基本上有三个输入Q、K和
So we're basically given three inputs Q and Q and
V。它们的形状基本上是T乘以D。在这里，
V. They are basically in shape of T times D. So here,
T是序列中的token数量，D是隐藏维度，
T is the number of tokens in a sequence, and D is the hidden dimension,
我们把Q、K、V分别叫做查询、键和值。
and we call QqV queries Ks and values.
然后记住，注意力本质上是在做加权求和，对吧？
And then remember attention essentially doing weighted sum, right?
所以在这里，加权求和基本上就是我们尝试对所谓的值进行加权求和。
So here, the weighted sum is basically we try to do a weighted sum over the so called values.
好，你可以看到这里是值，我们尝试用Q和K来计算那个S，就是ain平方。
Okay. You can see here is the values, and we try to use Q and K to compute that S, the ain square.
你可以看到ten平方在这里。
And you can see the ten square is here.
基本上我们是在操作如何计算ten平方。
It's basically we manipulate how we compute the ten square.
如果你看这个公式，我们是如何计算in平方的，
If you look at this equation, how we compute the in square,
基本上就是我们把Q和K相加来做一个嗯，对吧？
is basically we add Q and K to do a Mm, right?
然后我们用隐藏维度来归一化它。
And then we normalize it using the hidden dimension.
好，一旦我们做完这个，我们进一步用softmax来归一化它。
Okay. And once we do that, we further normalize it using soft max.
所以这些权重加起来等于一。
So the weights added into one.
事情是把方块加在一起，对吧？
The thing is square added into one, right?
然后我们用这些权重对数值进行加权求和，得到输出。
And then we use this weights to a weighted sum over the value and we get the output.
我们会一层一层地重复这个过程。
And we keep doing this layer by layer.
好的，有什么问题吗？
Okay. Any question?
我猜你们对这个很熟悉，对吧？
I assume you are very familiar with this, right?
很好。那么基本上，我们都用QT，比如小写的Q、K、V、T来表示
Cool. Okay. So basically, um, we all use QT, uh, like a small Q KTVT to refer to
K矩阵的RLT，好吗？
the RLT of the K matrix. Okay?
然后我们开始问一个问题，如何根据
And we start asking the question, how to compute the output HT based on
小写的QT和时间步T上的大矩阵来计算输出HT，好吗？
the small QT and the bigger matrix on timestep T, okay?
为了让打印更简单，我们会省略后缀To。
And to keep this printing simple, we will drop the suffix To We all
简单来说，用Q来指代QT的下一个切片，可以吗？
simply use Q to refer to QT next slice, okay?
所以我们基本上是在遵循这个公式，对吧？
So we are basically following this equation, okay?
从概念上讲，我们计算以下步骤的输出。
So conceptually, we compute the output of the following steps.
首先我们计算一个softmax之前的at平方，可以吗？
We first compute a pre soft max at in square, okay?
也就是我们取小Q和as，对吧，然后我们转置它。
Which is we take the small Q and the as okay, we transpose it.
然后我们做点积，并用某个常数项进行归一化。
Okay. And then we do a dot product and normalize by some constant term.
基本上我们得到了所谓的at平方，对吧？
And we basically get a so called at square, right?
这个平方是一个浮点数的平方。
This square is a floating point square.
它可以是任何值，明白吗？
It could be anything, okay?
但我们要做的是把它归一化到0到1的范围内。
But what do we do is we want to normalize it into, like, within a range 0-1.
所以我们基本上可以取一个加权和。
So we can basically take a weaty sum.
我们做的是取一个softmax，对吧？
So what we do is we take a softmax, okay?
我们取平方，然后用这个softmax进行归一化。
We take squares and we use this softmax to normalize it.
一旦归一化后，我们基本上对V的所有行做加权和，
Once we normalize it, we basically take a weighted sum over all the rows of V,
然后我们基本上就得到了输出。
and we basically get output
H。这基本上就是自注意力吗？
H. This is basically self atentin?
是的，直观上来说，SI计算的是QI与查询Q的相关性。
Yeah, intuition is basically SI computes the relevance of QI to the query Q.
然后我们对值做加权和，加权比例与相关性成正比。对。
And then we do weighted sum of the values proportional to the relevance. Yeah.
好的，当然，我们也可以把它写成矩阵形式。
Okay. And, of course, can, uh, write it in the matrix form.
如果你用矩阵形式写出来，基本上就是我们用Q和...
And if you write it in matrix form, it basically that we use Q and
K Q乘以Q的转置，对吗？
K Q times Q transpose, right?
而归一化因子是不变的。
And the normalizing factor is unchanging.
softmax基本上就是在行上进行归一化。
And soft max is basically like normalizing across the rows.
然后当我们得到那个十乘十的矩阵后，我们再和V相乘，就得到了输出。
And then once we get the ten square, we time it with V, and we get the output.
好的，有问题吗？很好，这很简单。
Okay. Any question? A good. This is simple.
好的，我记得在之前的课上，我们只讲了单一注意力机制，
Okay. I think in previous lecture, we only talk about a single attention,
但在Ms中，我们用的是多重注意力机制。
but in Ms, what we do is we use multi attention.
所以我们有很多很多，每一次的计算基本上，每个这样的面板都叫做一个头，
So we have many many And each computation is called basically each of this panel is called a head,
我们会并行地进行多次计算。
and we do multiple casts in parallel.
因此，我们的计算就多了一个维度，也就是头的数量。
Therefore, our computation has another dimension which is number of heads.
好的。这也非常直接。
Okay. This is also very straightforward.
直觉上，每个头可以对应不同类型的信息，
So the intuition is that each head can correspond to different kind of information,
有时候我们也可以共享头，比如说，
And sometimes we can share the heads, for example,
GQA 基本上就是所有的头共享 QV，但有不同的 Q。
GQA is basically like all has shared QV but have different Q.
好的。这就是多头注意力。
Okay. This thad attention.
我们也把多头注意力叫做 MHA。好的，明白了。
And we ala call Multi head attention MHA. Okay. Yeah.
如果你看 MHA，它基本上指的就是多头注意力。
If you look at MHA, it basically refers to Multi head attention.
好的，那我想我已经介绍完这个机制了。
Okay. Then I think I finished introducing they mechanism.
那你可能会想，我们到底是从哪里得到 Q、K 和 V 的，对吧？
Then you are probably wondering where exactly do we get Q and Q and V, right?
这其实也很简单。
So this is also simple.
所以，为了得到Q和Q，我们基本上是取前一个transformer层的输出
So in order to get Q and Q and, we basically take the output of the previous transformer layer
然后我们应用一个线性变换。
and we apply a linear information.
是的。在这里，我们引入了三个可学习的权重，
Yeah. Here, we introduce three learnable ways,
WQ、WK和WV。
WQ WK and WV.
对于第一层来说，这个X基本上就是输入。
And this X for the first layer, this x is basically input.
而对于中间层来说，这个X基本上就是前一层的输出，对吧？
And for the middle layer, this x is basically the output of the previous layer, okay?
然后我们基本上把它们结合在一起，得到QQV。
And we basically tie them together, we get QQV.
所以基本上QQV都是用不同的权重从输入转化而来的。
So basically QQV are all transposed from the input using different weights.
好的，明白了。
Okay. Cool.
好的，有了注意力机制，我们基本上可以开始揭示transformer模块了，对吧？
Okay. And with the attention, we can basically start revealing the uh, transformer block, right?
所以 transformer 块本质上是我们拿输入 X，嗯，做一个线性投影到
So transformer block is essentially we take the input X, um, we do a linear projection to
得到 QQV，然后我们拿到 QQV。
get the QQV then we take the QQV.
我们做自注意力机制，得到 Z。
We do the self attention. We get the Z.
然后我们进行一些逐元素归一化，通常是层归一化，但有时候
And we apply some element wise normalization, typically layer loam, but sometimes
我们也会用 RMS 归一化，好吗？
we also use RMS worm, okay?
然后我们会对它做一点转置，好吗？
And we transpose it a little bit, okay?
在这个层归一化之后，我们会引入一个两层的 MLP。
And after this layer loam, what we do is we introduce a two layer MLP.
好吗？我们经常这样做，对吧？两层 MLP，基本上就是两个矩阵乘法，好吗？
Okay? We have been doing this a lot, right two layer MLP, basically two matm, okay?
我们用这个矩阵乘法进一步转置它，最终通过
We use this matm to u transpose this further and eventually go through
另一个归一化，然后得到输出 edge。
another normalization and we get the output edge.
这个边基本上就是下一个变换层的输入。
And this edge is basically the input to the next transform layer.
好的，然后我们会一直这样做。有什么问题吗？
Okay. And we keep doing this. Okay. Any question?
很好，嗯，是的。
Cool. Um, yeah.
但实际上，就像我说的，当你训练语言模型时，
But in reality, like I said, when you train language model,
当你进行语言模型相关的计算时，你其实是在建模条件概率。
when you do language model kind of computation, uh, you are modeling the conditional probity.
你想要输出下一个条件或前一个标记的概率。
You want to output the probability of next to condition or pervious token.
然后当你输出下一个标记的概率时，
And then when you output the probability of next token,
你不希望、也不能看到未来的标记。
you don't want to you cannot see the future tokens.
但在训练时，你是知道未来标记的。
But when you do training, you did know the future tokens.
那你怎么办呢？你基本上会做这种掩码处理，对吧？
So what do you do you basically do this kind of masking, right?
你仍然计算遮罩方格，但你会屏蔽掉所有未来词元的遮罩方格。
You still compute the tenting square, but you mask out all the tenting squares of future tokens.
对吧？比如说，当你预测第一个词元的概率时，
Right? For example, when you predict the probability of the first token,
你只能看到第一个词元，其他什么都看不到，对吗？
you only see the first token, nothing else, right?
当你尝试预测第二个词元的概率时，你只能看到第一个和第二个词元。
When you try to predict the probity of second token, you only see the first and second token.
而其他词元位置的所有分数，你都无法看到。
And all scores on other token positions, you cannot see.
你实现的方法是使用遮罩操作。
The way you do it is you do masking.
但你可以更聪明一点，因为就像我说的，
But you can be a little bit smarter here because like I said,
如果你用遮罩，其实会浪费一些计算资源。
if you do masking, you are wasting some competition.
你在你的矩阵形式中，仍然在计算这个矩阵的所有元素，
You still in your matrix firm, you are still computing all the entries in this matrix,
但实际上你把它们扔掉了，因为你并没有用到它们。
but you are essentially throw away since you don't use them.
所以你可以变得更聪明一点，我们稍后会回到这个话题。
So you can be a little bit smarter, and we are going to come back to this.
好的，这就是掩码操作。
Okay, this is masking.
总结一下，transformer中我们关注解码器，因为解码器是
So in summary, transformer, we care about decoders because decoder is
语言模型中默认的transformer组件。
a default transformer component for the language models.
在语言模型中，我们有很多很多transformer解码器。
In language models, we have many many transformer decoders.
而这个transformer解码器实际上只是由注意力层和MLP组成的。
And in this transformer decoder is really just composed of attentions layer lo and MLP.
明白了吗？当然，我们的输入是一串token序列，对吧？
Okay? And of course, our input is a sequence of tokens, right?
所以我们需要把离散的token转换成向量，我们用的是嵌入。
So we need to transform a discrete token into a vector, and we use embedding.
所以我们有这个输入嵌入层。
So we have this input embedding.
好的，我们还关心token在序列中的相对位置。
Okay. And we also care about the relative position of token in the sequence.
我们还有一个位置嵌入，比如说，一个简单的位置嵌入可以是
We also have a position embedding, for example, a simple position embedding could
第一个标记为零，第二个标记为一，然后我基本上尝试
be the first token being zero, second token being one, and I try to basically
创建一个把01映射到另一个向量空间的嵌入。
create an embedding that 01 into another vector space.
但现在，我们的方法更加智能了。
But today, we are much smarter.
我们现在用的是一种叫做字面嵌入的嵌入方式，这里我就不详细讲了。
We are doing embedding called literal embedding, which I don't cover.
如果你感兴趣的话，可以去看看那篇论文。
If you're interested, you can basically take a look at that paper.
但本质上，我们有一个位置嵌入，用来告诉我们每个标记的具体位置。
But essentially, we have a position embedding to also tell us the exact position of each token.
好的。
Okay.
最后，我们基本上会经过这一层，输入嵌入，位置嵌入。
And finally, we basically go through this layer, input embedding, positing embedding.
多头注意力，几次残差加法，两层MLP，残差，然后重复这个过程。
Multi hitension a few roman additions, two layer MLP, romanidon and we repeat.
好的，我们重复多次，这就等于有多层网络。
Okay, we repeat in times, and it's equals to a number of layers.
然后我们把它投影回到token空间。
And then we project it back into the token space.
我们将token与观测到的token进行比较，计算损失。
We compare the token to the observe token calculate the loss.
这就是我们的损失函数，softmax。
That is our loss function, softmax.
明白了吗？这本质上就是transformers，语言模型。对吧。
Okay? This is essentially transformers, language models. Okay. Yeah.
在这四层中，就像我说的，本质上是一个两层的MLP，
And in this four layers, like I said, it's essentially a two layer MLP,
你有输入X乘以权重矩阵再加上偏置。
where you have input X times weight matrix plus bias.
得到结果后，你再用一个线性函数，
And once you get the results, you take a linear function,
u或者其他什么，再乘以另一个权重W2加上偏置。
u or something else, time another with W two plus a bias.
对，很简单。我们已经做过很多很多次了，对吧？
Yeah, simple. We have been doing this many, many times, right?
好的。
Okay.
好的，那我们来分解一下，比如说，计算组件有哪些？
Okay. Then let's break it down, into, like, what are the computing components?
计算组件基本上就是，我们有自注意力，对吧。
The computing components is basically, we have self attention, right.
我们有层和残差。
We have layer and residual.
我们有MLP，我们有长线性层。
We have MLPs, we have long linear.
显然你已经学过这种逐层残差线性操作，它们是逐元素操作，
Apparently you have learned this layer wise residual linear, they are element wise operations light,
只会带来很少的浮点运算，非常容易处理。
leading just a little bit of flops, very easy to deal with.
但是自注意力非常慢。
But self attention very slow wipe.
这个我稍后会讲。
I will cover this later.
MLP也很慢，因为它的参数量很大，矩阵运算非常耗时。
MLP is very slow we because it's metams big metam and metamo is taking a lot of
计算所需的浮点运算量你们已经知道了怎么打开metal。我们这部分也没问题。
flops to compute and you guys already know how to open metal. We are also good with this part.
你们已经了解那个内核了。好的，很棒。
You already know that kernel. Okay, cool.
至少为了优化RM，
In order to optimize the RM, at least,
我觉得我们唯一的问题就是自注意力机制，
I think we only have one problem is self attention,
我们下周会讲这个。
W cover next week.
还有我们有词嵌入，但词嵌入本质上就是另一个内存操作。
And also we have a word embedding, but the word embedding essentially another memo.
查找表。对，非常简单。
Look up table. Yeah, very simple.
我们还有位置嵌入，这也非常简单。
And we have position embedding, which is also very simple.
没有额外的浮点运算。损失函数，
No flops. Loss function,
Softmax。你们也已经实现过这个。
Softmax. You also implement this.
好吗？不，我们来分解这个M，对吧？
Okay? No, we break this M down, right?
所以基本上，从计算的角度来看，现在唯一的问题基本上就是自注意力，
So basically, from computing perspective, the only problem now is basically self attention,
如何让它变快，明白吗？
how to make it fast, okay?
就像我说的，像TBD R这样的模型，或者所有这类模型。
And like I said, models like TBD R or all these kind of models.
他们做的事情基本上就是重复这些transformatic co层。
So what they do is basically, they repeat these kind of transformatic co layers.
输入是一个序列，他们不断在MLP中执行自注意力。
Okay, the input is a sequence, and they keep performing self attent in the MLPelf MLP.
他们重复很多很多次，然后得到一个预测结果。
They repeat many, many times and they get a prediction.
好的。
Okay.
根据不同类型的模型，不同的实现方式，
And depending on different kind of model, kind of implementation,
他们基本上可以做一些小的改变，但只是很小的差别。
they can basically change a little bit, but very small Delta.
好吗？比如说，这是最初的Transformer论文，这是Matas Lama，
Okay? For example, this is the original transformer paper, and this is Matas Lama,
唯一的区别至少在这里。
and the only difference is at least here.
比如说，你插入层的位置，
So for example, where you insert the layer loam,
你可以在注意力之前插入层，也可以在注意力之后插入层。
you could insert layer before tenting or after attention.
这就叫做后层或者前层。明白吗？
Okay? That is called post layer or pre layer m. Okay.
但就像我说的，计算量并不会有太大变化，因为它只是一个层。
But like I said, the computing doesn't change a lot because it's a layer loon.
好的。还有你要用哪种归一化方法？
Okay. Also what kind of normalization you are going to use?
有些用LayerNorm，有些用RMSNorm。
Some use layer. So use RMS norm.
我觉得你已经在你的作业环境里实现了这个。
I think you implement this one in your homework environment.
对，还有线性函数是什么？
Yeah. Also what is the lininear function?
原本是Valu，但lama用的是sl。
The originalm is Valu, but lama use sl.
SLO和它们非常相似。
SLO and are very similar.
轻量级的线性函数。
Light linear functions.
还有位置编码，基本上就是位置嵌入。
And also position encoding is basically the position embedding.
我们可能用的是不同类型的后置嵌入，但依然非常轻量。
Like we probably use different kind of post embeddings, but still very light.
你可以从这个表格看到，计算量大的部分变化不大，
You can see from this table, you can see the compute heavy part doesn't change a lot,
所以基本上就是MLP和注意力机制。他们一直用这些。
so it's basically MLP and tension. They always use that.
好的。在训练时，我们基本上是观察整个序列，对吧。
Okay. And when training, what we do is basically, um, we observe the entire sequence, right.
但我们的模型只能预测下一个token，而不是整个序列。
But our model is only capable of predicting the next token, not the entire sequence.
所以我们基本上把整个序列的概率分解成
So we basically decompose that uh probability of the entire sequence into
这是许多条件的分解，对吧？
a factoring of many conditions, right?
所以我们基本上做的就是，把这个序列输入到RM中
So what do we do is basically, um, like we fit this sequence into RM
然后我们在每一个输出位置进行预测，对吧？
and we predict at each output position, right?
当我们预测这个位置，也就是第二个词时，我们会把剩下的词都遮蔽起来。
And when we predict this position, the second word, we are masking the rest of the words.
明白吗？我们只看第一个词，就是这个，然后尝试预测第二个词。
Okay? We only look at the first word, this one, and we try to predict the second word.
一旦我们有了预测结果，我们就把这个预测和该位置实际观察到的词进行比较。
And once we have a prediction, we compare this predict to the exact observed word at that position.
我们计算损失，对吧？
We calculate loss, right?
同样的，当我们预测这个词时，只允许我们看这两个词。
And same thing, when we predict this word, we only are allowed to look at these two words.
我们就是做这种遮蔽操作。
And we do that kind of masking.
这里比较漂亮、比较好的地方是，
And the pretty thing, the nicer thing here is,
你可以一次性完成这个，对吧？
You can do this in one pass, right?
你在每个位置都在计算损失，但其实可以一次性完成，
You are calcat loss at each position, but you can do this in one pass,
因为就像我说的，注意力机制是高度可并行的。
because you are basically doing like I said, attention is highly paralyzable.
所以无论你在任何位置计算注意力分数时，基本都可以直接进行计算。
So whenever you compute the atten scored at any position, you can basically do the computation.
你不需要依赖之前的隐藏状态。
You don't have to depend on the previous hidden states.
如果你把这种变换改成RNN，就不是这样了，因为你必须
If you change this transformation into a iron, that's not the case, because you have to
预测一个token，然后再预测下一个token。
predict one token, the next toenxt.
这就是为什么注意力机制非常适合GPU。
That's why attention is super good for GPUs.
有什么问题吗？好吧。那我们开始今天的主要内容，好吗？好的。
Any question? Okay. Okay, then let's start our major topic, okay, for this part. Okay.
这只是一个回顾，好吗？
This is just a recap, okay?
所以我们现在在做机器学习系统，对吧。
So we are doing machine learning systems, right.
我们已经讨论过张量，也讨论过transformers。
So we know we have talk about tension, talk about transformers.
但我们真正关心的其实就是几个问题，对吧？
But the real thing we care about is basically a few questions, right?
比如说，它的计算特性。
Like, it's computing characteristics.
我想我已经给你们讲过这样的一个模型，当你开始分析
So I think I already give you this kind of like a model when you start taking
机器学习程序时，你关心三件事。
machine learning program to analyze. You care about three things.
一个是计算，另一个是内存，还有一个是通信。
One is computer, another is memory, another is communication.
你关心计算，是因为你需要知道我需要花多少浮点运算，对吧？
You care about computer because you need to know how many flops I need to spend, right?
你关心内存，是因为你不能超过GPU的峰值内存，
You care about memory because you cannot exceed the peak memory GPs,
你关心通信，是因为你想要并行化，对吧？
and you care about communication because you want to paralyze it, okay?
因此，为了分析这三个特性，我们首先需要理解一些事情。
So in order to analyze these three charcistics, we need to basically understand a few things.
第一件事是我们需要能够计算语言模型的参数数量。
The first thing is we need to be able to calculate the number parameters of language model.
为什么？因为这很重要。
Why? Because it matters.
至少我们需要分配足够的内存来存储这些参数。
At least we need to allocate that amount of memory to store the parameters.
所以基本上，如果我给你一个语言模型，你需要知道它有多少参数。
So basically, I give you a language model, you need to know how many parameters it has.
这将决定你存储该模型所需的最小存储空间。
So that will determine the minimum storage you use to store that model.
明白了吗？当然，当你开始进行通信，开始做分布式处理时，
Okay? And of course, when you start doing communication when you start doing partism
有时候你需要根据宽度来划分，比如运算符的宽度，或者在计算图中的宽度。
sometimes you partition over the width the width operators, the width in the Delph graph.
通过知道宽度有多大，你就知道该如何划分。
And by knowing how large the width is, you know how to partition.
好的，明白了吗？第二台计算机，对吧？
All right. Okay. Second computer, right?
要了解一台计算机，你需要知道完成RM程序需要多少次浮点运算，对吧？
In order to know a computer, you need to know how many flops
也就是说，完成RM程序需要多少次浮点运算，对吧？
needed to finish the completion of the RM program, right?
好吗？所以基本上，这个基本上决定了所需的计算机，好吗？
Okay? So basically, this basically, um, determines the computer needed, okay?
你需要能够估算完成这个程序需要多少台计算机。
You need to be able to estimate how many computer needed to finish this program.
当然，你还需要能够估算需要多少内存。
And, of course, you need to be able to estimate the memory, how many memory needs.
就像我说的，内存与几个方面有关，一个当然是参数数量。
And like I said, memory is associated with a few since one is, of course, lumber parameters.
另一个基本上是内部的中间激活状态，还有最优状态。
The other is basically internal intermediate activations, and optimal states, also,
这也涉及到通信，因为如果你选择对激活状态进行分区，
this kind of, you get involved with communication because if you choose to partition the activation,
你也会影响需要进行多少次通信，
you also, well, basically influence how many communication you need to conduct
在不同的GPU之间。
between different, uh, GPUs.
好的。那么从计算的角度来看，这里有三个核心问题需要理解。
Okay. So three core questions here to understand from a computing perspective.
第一个是如何估算参数数量。
The first is how to estimate the number parameters.
第二个是估算浮点运算次数。
The second is estimate the flops.
第三个是估算内存需求。
Third is estimate the memory needs between
一旦我们理解了这些，我们就知道如何进行并行化。
R. And once we understand this, we know how to paralyze it.
我们知道应该分配多少资源给它。
We know how many to allocate to it.
我们也知道应该分配多少存储空间。
And we also know how many storage we allocate to storage with.
好的，我们一个一个来做。
Okay, let's do that one by one.
这非常重要，所以我会深入细节讲解。
And this is so important that I'm going to dive into details and I'm
我还会给你们布置相关的作业。
also going to give you homework to do this.
好的。第一个问题，如何计算M的参数数量？我们来一步步分析。
Okay. First question, how to calculate the number of parameters of M? Let's go through it.
所以这是RMs的计算，对吧？我们一个个来看。
So this is RMs computation, right? Let's go one by one.
好的，呃，我们有一个输入X，对吧，这个输入X是
Okay. Uh, we have a input X, right, and this input X is going
基本上会经过嵌入层，对吧？
to basically being go through embedding layer, right?
嵌入层的作用其实就是把每个token嵌入到一个向量中。
So the embedding layer, what it does is basically embeach token into a vector.
好的，所以计算方式是这样的。
Okay? So commutation is looking like this.
我们拿到一个token，首先把它转成one-hot编码，对吧？
We take a token. We first transform the token into one hot, right?
这个one-hot向量的大小就是词表的大小，对吧？
And the size of this one hot vector is the size of the vocabulary, right?
然后我们用这个one-hot向量和我们的嵌入矩阵相乘。
And then we basically multiply this one hot with our embedding matrix.
我们就得到了向量。好的，这就是第一层。
We get the vector. Okay? First layer.
一旦我们有了向量，我们就有了一系列的向量。
Once we have the vector, we have a sequence of vectors.
每个向量的维度是D或者H，或者说每个向量都有一个维度，我们有一个向量序列。
Each vector is of dimension D or H or each vector is of dimension and we have a sequence
向量序列，同步的S。
of vectors. Synchronized S.
当然，我们还有一个外部维度，就是批量大小，也就是序列的数量，所以我们有一个B。
Of course, we have a outer dimension, which is a backside, number of sequences, so we have a B.
好的，这里我选择了一个执行预归一化的语言模型，
Okay. And here I choose a language model which performs pre mannisation,
这意味着一旦它进入这个transformer层，
which means that once it enters into this transformer layer,
它会在层内执行归一化操作。
it will perform romanization layer loam.
我想你们已经知道在作业中layer norm是怎么做的，所以我就跳过这部分。
And I think you already know how layer loom does in homework. I'm going to skip that.
layer norm里面有一些参数，对吧。
Layer lo inside of linear loom is are a few parameters, right.
好的，当你完成layer norm后，形状还是BSH，对吗？
Okay. And once you finish layer loam, what's the shape? Still BSH. Okay?
记住这一点，BSH基本上是黄金法则，手臂中的许多边界，基本上都是BSH。
Remember this, BSH is basically the golden rule, many boundaries in the arms, basically BSH.
明白了吗？所以这里我要用BSH，然后进入自注意力，对吧？
Okay? So here I'm going to have a BSH I'm going to go into self attention, right?
在自注意力中。
And in self attention.
那你有哪些参数呢？
So what parameters do you have?
首先你要把这个PSH投影到QQ上。
You first project this PSH into QQ.
为了做投影，你有三个矩阵WQ、WK和WV。
In order to do the projection, you have three metric WQ WK and WV.
这里你有三个参数，就是这些。
Here you have three parameters, this.
一旦你做了投影，接下来做什么？你做自注意力。
Once you do the projection, what do you do? You do self attention.
你用Q乘以K转置，归一化，softmax，然后用V加权求和，就完成了。
You Q times K transports normalization soft max, then we is sum, you're done.
你可以看到，在这个过程中，没有更多的参数了。
You can see through this process, there's no more parameters.
只有三个参数 W W WV。这样我们就可以了。
Only three parameters W W WV. Then we are good.
这里我们只是在继续参数。
Here we are only continuing parameters.
好的，好，好，好。
Okay, good, good, good.
然后我们进入下一层的归一化，你知道的，我就跳过了。
And then we go through the next layer mization and you know it, I'm going to skip it.
好的，一旦你完成了那一层，你就进入MLP，对吧？
Okay, once you finish layer later, you enter MLP, right?
在MLP中，就像我说的，基本上是两层的MLP，并且有一个线性函数
In MLP, like I said, it's basically two layer MLP, and there's a ln linear function
在这两层MLP之间。
between these two layer MLP.
那么在MLP中，你有哪些参数？
So in MLP, what parameter do you have?
两个权重和两个偏置，非常简单，对吧？
To arithmetrics, and two biases, very simple, right?
好的，当你完成MLP后，你会再做一次归一化。再一层。
Okay. And once you finish MLP, you do another romanization. Another layer.
是的。不好意思，一旦你完成前向传播，你会多次重复这个过程，次数取决于层数。
Yeah. Sorry, once you finish fit forward, repeat you repeat many times number layers.
这个次数是由层数和层的数量决定的。
And this is determined by the number of layers and layers.
一旦你完成了这些变换层的次数，基本上就进入了另一个层的归一化过程。
And once you finish these times of trans layers, you basically enter another layer romanization
稍微归一化一下，然后你会进入另一个反向嵌入。
to romanize a little bit, and then you'll go into another reverse embedding.
基本上，你会拿你的嵌入向量，并尝试把它投射回词汇表中，明白吗？
Basically, you take your embedding and you try to project it back into the vocabulary, okay.
在很多很多语言模型的实现中，这个嵌入和那个嵌入它们
And in many many language model implementations, this embedding and this embedding they
是共享的，使用的是同一个嵌入。
are shared, same embedding.
所以你不会引入任何新的参数。
So you don't introduce any new parameters.
你用的是最初的嵌入。
You use the original embedding.
在huggingface中，这被称为时间嵌入。
And hug in phase is called time embedding.
好的。在很多很多情况下，time body 是启用的。
Okay. And in many, many cases, it's time body is enabled.
没错。好的，最后你进入 softmax，计算你的损失。
It's true. Okay. And finally, you enter softmax, you calculate your loss.
明白了吗？我基本上带你走完了整个参数计数的过程，对吧？
Okay? I basically took you through this entire parameter counting process, right?
所以有一点点不同。
So a little bit difference.
在一些模型中，尤其是现代模型中，我们基本上让那个 MLP
In some models, especially in modern models, we are basically making that MLP
变得更复杂了一些。
a little bit more complicated.
我们在使用这个 suit GLU，而 sued GLU 和
We are using this suit GLU, and the only difference between the sued GLU and
MLP 唯一的区别是我们要引入另一个宽度矩阵。
the MLP is we are going to introduce another wid matrix.
我们会取注意力机制的输出。
We are going to take the output of the attention.
首先我们做一次线性变换，然后再做这个 switch 变换。
We first do a linear transformation, and then we do this switch transformation,
然后我们再进行一次线性变换，并对它们做点积。
and then we have another linear transformation, and we do a dot product between them.
接着我们进入第三层，MLP W三。
Then we go through a third layer, MLP W three.
所以这有点像amass架构，好吧，Sug EIU。
So this is kind of like the amass architecture, okay, Sug EIU.
正如你所看到的，如果你进行比较的话
So as you can see, if you compare
SWOU和传统的MLP相比，你引入了一个新的参数，
SWOU and traditional MLP, you are introducing one more parameter,
多了一个权重矩阵，明白了吗？记住这个。
one more weight matrix. Okay? Remember this?
是的，从两个方面来看。
Yeah, Quest in two ways.
是的，但通常在这之后，我们还会有另一层。
Yeah. But usually after this, we have another layer.
嗯，明白了，对吧？
Yeah. Okay. Makes sense, right?
很好。那么如果你开始计算参数数量，
Cool. Okay. If you start counting the parameters,
我基本上把它放在这里，嵌入层，它的形状是词汇表
I basically put it here, Embedding layers, the shape is vocabulary
大小乘以隐藏维度，对吧？
size times heating dimension, right?
所以这些是你的Lama参数。
So this is your lamer parameters.
Leyenon基本上就是d维度。
Leyenon is basically d dimension.
你有一个单独的参数用来进行罗马化。
You have a single parameter which you use to romanize.
好吗？自注意力机制，有多少个参数？
Okay? Self attention, how many?
这就是Lama的情况。
So this is the Lama case.
在Lama的情况下，你要做的是有WQ，
So in Lama case, what do you do is you have WQ,
WK和WV这三个参数，并且它们的形状是一样的，
WK and WV there's three, and they are of the same shape,
它们可以把你从一个维度转置到另一个维度，对吧？
which transpose you from edge to edge, right?
所以这是三条边的平方。
So this is three edges square.
好的。但是在ama中，注意力机制之后你会做什么，
Okay. But in ama, what do you do after attention,
你会再做一次外部投影。明白了吗？
you are going to do another outer projection. Okay.
是的，如果你查一下ama。
Yeah, if you check ama.
所以基本上，在注意力机制之后，我们还有一次外部投影，
So basically, after attention, we have another outer projection which
会对边到边再做一层变换。
do another layer of transformation from edge to edge.
所以你又有了一个边的平方。
So you have another edge square.
所以实际上，在自注意力机制中，你有这么多参数。
So in total, in practice for self attention, you have this number of parameters.
明白了吗？
Okay? Does that make sense?
好，你可能会问，在自注意力机制中，为什么要用多头注意力，对吧？
Okay, you probably ask in self attention, why are you using multi head attention, right?
所以我们实际上有多个头。
So we actually have multiple heads.
那为什么这个还是逐边进行的呢？
So why this is, um, still edge by edge?
为什么这个WQ投影是从边到边的？
Why this project WQ is projecting from edge to edge?
还是不想回答。
A still don't want to answer.
这是因为本质上头的数量乘以头的维度，还是
It's because essentially mart head the lumber head, times the head size is still
等于边。这是一个约束条件。
equal to edge. Yeah, that's a constraint.
你实际上是先投影到另一个空间，你首先应用
You are essentially projected into another you first apply
这个WQ把向量从边投影到边，然后再分成不同的头。
this WQ project a vector from edge to edge, and then you split into different heads.
是的。我在语言模型中也是这么做的。
Yeah. That's what I do for language models.
好的。所以这里参数的数量并没有改变。
Okay. So it doesn't change the number of parameters here.
然后你继续进行midion，这是另一个隐藏维度。
Then you continue doing midion which is another hidden dimension.
你做的是前馈。那么这里，前馈中有多少参数？
You do fit forward. So here, how many parameters in fit forward?
对于单个矩阵来说，基本上是H乘以I，H是输入维度。
So for a single matrix is basically, uh, H times I H is the input dimension.
I是输出维度。
I is output dimension.
所以在GBD三中，I等于4H。
So I GBD three, I equals to four edge.
这意味着你在做上投影。
Which means that you are doing upper projection.
你把隐藏维度从H投影到4H，然后再投影回来。
You project the hidden dimension from edge to four edge, and you project it back.
但就像我说的，在Lama中你用的是sua GLU，所以你有三个这样的结构，对吧？
But like I said, in Lama you do sua GLU, so you house three of them, right?
所以这就是为什么这个数字是三的平方。
So that's why this number is three square.
抱歉，是三乘以H乘以I，而I等于4H，所以是12H平方。
Sorry, it's three Hi, and I equals to four H, so it's 12 edges square.
很多参数，对吧？
A lot of primeters, right?
然后你继续对这些词汇做罗马化处理。
And then you continue doing roman edition on this vocabulary.
就像我说的，这个和这个是一样的，所以我们不重复计算。
Like I said, this one is the same with this one, so we don't count, we don't double count.
好的。好的。这基本上就是你作业的解答，好吗？
Okay. Okay. This is basically a solution to your homework, okay?
试着实现一下这个，很酷。
Try to implement this cool.
有什么问题吗？好，现在让我问你一个问题，你看这个。
Any question? Okay. Now, let me ask you a question, you look at this.
你看，这就是我已经给你的RM的一个参数。
You look at. This is a parameter of RMs, I already give you.
几乎90%的RM基本上都是这样的。
Almost like 90% of RM basically like this.
我的问题是，当你尝试扩展RM时，你会在哪一部分
My question is when you try to scale up RM, which part you are going to see
看到参数方面的瓶颈？
the bottleneck in terms of parameters?
你最有可能遇到瓶颈的前两个地方是哪里？
Which are the top two places you are likely to see a bottleneck?
第一个是哪里？没错，就是这个。
Which is the first one? Absolutely, this one.
就像我说的，你在做的是I乘以I再乘以三。
Like I said, you are doing times I times three.
而且就像我说的，在大多数情况下，
And like I said, in most cases,
I就像是一个四维边。
I is like a four edge.
所以当你尝试扩展语言模型的规模时，你实际上是在扩展隐藏层的边数，
So when you try to scale the size of language model, you ally scale the hidden size edge,
而这个部分增长得最快的是
and this one grows the most is
12乘以边的平方再平方到边。
12 edges square's square to edge.
所以如果你试图扩大你的模型，这一部分会急剧增加。
So if you try to enlarge your model, this one is going to explode.
你的大量参数都会集中在ML部分。
You are going to have a lot of parameters concentrated at the ML piece.
好的。这也为我们在Mcatron中进行分区提供了另一个理由，
Okay. This also provides another argument why in Mcatron we
因为在某个阶段，我们会尝试扩展语言模型，
are partitioning this because at some point, we will try to skew language model
而这个部分会最先爆炸。
and this one will explode first.
一旦它爆炸了，唯一让它继续适配的方法基本上就是做分区并行，
And once it exploded, the only way to steal make it fit is basically doing partitioning parallelism,
也就是如何用矩阵来分区。
how to partition this with matrix.
如果还记得，在Mctron我们的模型里，我们就是这样分区的，这是数学模式。
If remember in Mctron our model we do is we partition in this way, this is the math mode.
我们在第一个输入X上做列分区，在权重W上做分区，然后这里得到一个部分和。
We column part in the first input X, we party in the width W, and here we get a partial sum.
这是因为当我们尝试扩展语言模型时，这个部分会爆炸。
That's because when we try to scale language model, this one explode.
是的，我们必须对它进行分区。
Yeah, we have to part it.
那么，第二个可能爆炸的地方在哪里？
Where is the second place that this can get exploded?
是的，自注意力机制。
Yes, self attention.
你可以看到这里有很多参数。
You can see there's a lot of parameters.
所以基本上，语言模型参数的主要来源就是这个。
So basically, the primary sources of language model parameters come from this
这是第一大因素，这是第二大因素。
is the number one factor, this is number two factor.
这就是为什么所有关于参数的策略基本上都是
That's why all the part strategies for parameters basically are basically
针对这两个部分做一些调整。
performing some pis on these two parts.
是的，其他部分其实并不重要，你可以从这些数学公式中看出来。
Yeah. Other parts are not important at all, you can see from these equations mathematics. Okay.
抱歉，什么？你问什么问题？
Sorry, what's that? What's the question?
是这个吗？不好意思。
Is it? This one. Sorry.
好的，抱歉。现在你明白参数的动态变化了。
Yeah, sorry. Now, you understand the dynamics of parameters.
在P三中，特别是在skinny law那一节，你需要实现这个函数。
And in P three, especially in the skinning law section, you need to implement this function
用来计算参数数量，你也会明白为什么Lama 7B是7B。
to count number parameters, and you are going to understand why Lama seven B is seven B.
为什么Lama 30是30。
Why Lama 30 is 30.
你要进行参数计数，这样你才有参考依据，因为如果
You are going to count that you have a reference because if
你不是在Opothirty，那就是错的，对吧？
you are not at Opothirty are wrong, right?
好的，酷。那我们让它更复杂一点。
Okay. Cool. Okay. Let's make it more complicated.
参数很简单，因为参数只有几个。
Parameter is easy because there are just a few parameters.
那么flops呢，计算量呢？
How about flops, compute.
我们需要多少计算量？我们来试试。
How many computer we need? Let's do it.
好，总结一下。我觉得我已经讲过了，如何估算计算量？
Okay. Recap. I think I covered this, what is how do I estimate compute?
主要是因为其他操作符都比较轻量。
Mostly meto because other operators are pretty light.
所以我们只在这个等式里计算矩阵乘法的次数。
So we just count matms MMO is this equation,
M乘以H再乘以1，但这个乘以1可以忽略。
M times H times one, but this Mus one can be ignored.
基本上，任何矩阵乘法基本上都是两个M，M是第一个维度，
Basically, for any matrix multiplication is basically two M and where M is the first dimension,
NH是第二个维度。
NH is the second dimension.
我会像之前一样给你一些符号说明，
Is I'm going to give you a few notations like I did before,
B等于B序列长度为S。
B equal to B sequence length as
Lambert的隐藏状态大小是100D。
Lambert has hidden state size of 100 D.
就像我说的，当D和它们绑定在一起时，它们等于H，对吧？
And like I said, D, when they tied together, they equal to edge, right?
好的，Suu投影维度I在大多数情况下等于4H，对不起，是词汇表大小。
Okay. Suu project dimension I, in most cases, are equal to four edge, sorry, vocabulary size, okay?
一旦我们有了这些维度，我们就来计算一下flops。
Once we have these dimensions, let's do the flops calculation.
这会帮助你理解为什么Lama需要1000GB来训练30天。
And this will help you understand why Lama needs 1,000 GB to train 30 days.
好的，酷。我们一步一步来。
Okay, cool. Let's do it one by one.
首先，我有X作为输入，我什么都不做，因为它是输入，所以没有flops，
First, I have X as input, and I do nothing because it's input, so there's no flops,
但是形状是BSH，然后我通过了embedding。
but the shape is BSH, then I go through the embedding.
我觉得embedding相当轻量。
I think embedding is pretty light.
好的，那我就不算它了。
Okay, I don't count it.
然后我进入自注意力机制，为了执行自注意力的第一步，
And then I enter self attention and in order to perform the first step of self attention,
我做了这个投影。
I do this projection.
基本上，我有BSH，然后
Basically, I have B SH and
我从边到边进行投影，BS并没有变化。
I'm projecting from edge to edge and BS is not changing.
所以对于每一个，met moo 基本上就是两个B平方。
So for each, met moo is basically two B square.
明白了吗？我基本上是在用我的方程，而且我做了三次，对吧？
Okay? I'm basically using my equation, and I do it three times, right?
QQV。明白了吗？所以flop就是乘以三。
QQV. Okay? So the flop is times three.
很好。然后我有一个位置嵌入，就是rope。
Good. Then I have a position embedding which is the rope.
但rope其实很简单。
But the rope is pretty simple.
基本上这个方程就是在这些东西上做一些线性变换。
It's basically this equation is basically some linear transformation on top of the things.
我没有详细讲，但它其实很轻量，因为你可以看到，
I don't cover it, but it's pretty light because you can see,
这里有一个平方，这里没有平方。
there's a square here and there's no square here.
你可以想象这个比这个大很多，然后我再做softmax。
You can imagine it is much bigger than this one, then I do this soft max,
这是一个复杂的部分。
this is a complicated part.
所以我这里有两个术语。
So I have two terms here.
第一个术语是我需要做Q乘以K，Q的形状是什么？
The first term is I need to do Q times K, what is the shape of Q?
是BSH，K也是BSH。
It's BSH K is also BSH.
这里的归约是H，以及如何操作。
The reduction that means is H, and how to.
所以你可以看到浮点运算量变成了这样，明白吗？
So therefore, you can see the flops become this. Okay?
如果你把它放进去，我希望你注意一下。
And if you put it, I want you to pay attention.
如果你把它代入，你会发现这个项非常糟糕。
And if you put it into this, you'll find that this term is pretty bad.
为什么？你有S的平方。
Why? You have S square.
那么S是什么？是序列长度。
So what is S? Sequence lens.
这意味着每当你尝试建模更长的序列时，
That means whenever you try to model a longer sequence,
你的计算量会以二次方增长。
you are going to quadratically increase your flops.
现在，你明白了n连接问题。
Now, you understand the n connect problem.
如果我想建模一百万长度的连接，那就是一百万的平方。那么我需要多少计算量？
If I want to model 1 million connect lens, this is 1 million square. So how many flops I need?
我不知道，几乎是无限的，对吧？
I don't know. Infinite almost, right?
所以注意力机制在序列长度上表现得相当糟糕，对吧？
So attention is pretty bad on sequence lens, right?
因为我有第二项，三P平方N，这很简单，因为
As I have a second term three Ps square N, and this is easy because it's
基本上我就是做softmax，
basically I basically take softmax,
我取指数，然后再做归一化，对吧？
I take the exponential and then I divide the unimalization, right?
好的，最后，当我得到softmax P时，这是一个平方，归一化的注意力平方。
Okay. And finally, after I get the softmax P, this is a square, normalized atten square.
我再做一次矩阵乘法，这次是对这些值求和。
I do another matrix multiplication that is wit sum, o over the values.
这又是另一个类似的操作，对B来说是平方和D。很糟糕，对吧？又是一个a的平方项。
And this is another metimo which is to B as square and D. Pretty bad, right? Another a squared term.
好的，非常非常糟糕。Aten真的太贵了，我现在明白了。
Okay, very, very bad. Okay, Aten is so expensive. Now I understand.
最后，我有一个超投影，就像我之前提到的，这是另一个操作。
And finally, I have a ultra projection, like I mentioned, is another
我把BSH拿出来投影一次。
I take a BSH and project it once.
这是标准的2B S平方。
And this is the standard two B s square.
我会说B H平方比B S平方好得多，因为H是
I would say B H squared is much better than B S squared Because H is
模型的隐藏状态大小，这个我无法控制。
the hidden state of the model size, I can't control it.
但S是序列长度，这个我也无法控制。
But S is a sequence, I cannot control it.
我想要建模无限长的序列。对吧？
I want to model infinitely long sequences. Yeah. Okay?
所以你可以看到这个项是没问题的。
So you can see this term is okay.
这个也相当不错。
This one is pretty good.
好的，然后，当然，
Okay. And then, of course,
我有一个残差连接是这样的，这个残差基本上就是加法，
I have a residual connection like this, and this residual is basically addition,
所以这14个点BSH很简单。
so the 14 points BSH easy.
你看这基本上揭示了注意力所需的浮点运算量，你已经提前透露了问题，
See this basically reveal the flops needed for attention and you already spoil the problem,
我们之后会回来解决这个问题。
and we are going to come back to fix this problem.
让我们继续，我们要进入MLP部分。
Let's continue. We are going to enter the MLP.
在MLP中，输入基本上就是自注意力的输出，是PSH。
In MLP, the input input is basically the output of self attention, It's PSH.
好的，我们都假设是ama，也就是适合GLU。
Okay. And we all assume is ama, which is suit GLU.
那我们就这样做，对吧？
So we do this, right?
我们首先做一个门控投影，然后做上投影。
We first do a gate projecting, we do upper projection.
所以我们有这个项，然后乘以二，因为有两次，
So we have this term and we time two because twice,
好的，然后我们有激活操作。
Okay then we have activation.
激活其实很简单。
Activation is pretty simple.
好的，元素Y也很简单。
Okay. Element Y is pretty simple.
然后我们有一个下投影，这又是一个矩阵乘法，B乘以S乘以I。
And then we have a down projection, which is another matmT B SH, I.
这个I是隐藏维度。
This I is the hidden dimension.
就像我说的，I等于四倍的H。
Like I said, I equal to four H.
所以你可以看到这两个项，它们其实也有问题，因为它们
So you can see these two terms, they are also problematic because they have
上面有一个平方项，对吧？
a square term on top of it, right?
但对于其他元素来说，没有平方项，完全是线性的。
But for other element is, there's no square term. It's pure linear.
好的。所以这意味着这两个将是主要的计算量来源。
Okay. So that means that this two will be the primary source of flops.
好的。最后，我在所有分支上应用了一些层，但没关系，因为它们都很简单。
Okay. And finally, I apply some layer on all arms but which is okay because they're pretty simple.
好的。
Okay.
对这张幻灯片有什么问题吗？如果没有，我们可以把所有内容整合起来。
Any questions on this slide? Okay, then we can put everything together.
所以语言模型的总计算量，基本上就是你要计算注意力部分。
So the total flops of language model is basically you count the tension.
你还要计算swigOU。
You count the swigOU.
把它们加在一起，然后乘以层数，对吧？
You put them together, you times the number of layers, right?
再加上嵌入部分，就得到了这个公式。
And you plus embedding, you get this equation.
问题？这是屏幕法则第二部分的答案。
A question? This is the answer to the second part of screen law.
你将要实现这个。而且还有
You are going to implement this. And there are also
参考资料，因为你可以去查TPD编号的论文。
reference because you can go check TPD number paper.
他们告诉你需要多少次浮点运算，然后你写这个函数，如果你做不到，
They told you how many flops you need, and you write this function and you can't.
如果你的数字和他们的不一样，那就说明你错了，对吧？好的，明白了。
And if your number is not equal to the number, that means you are wrong, right? Okay. Okay, cool.
好的，如果我们把一些数值代入这个方程，假设我们用的批量等于
Okay. And if we basically substitute a few values into this equation, assuming we use a batch equal
一，也就是单个序列。
to one, that is a single sequence.
这是Lama 27b的规格说明。
And this is the specification from Lama 27b.
我们得出结论，为了进行一次前向传播，我们需要这些浮点运算。
And we basically get that in order to basically perform a single forward pass, we need these flops.
而这个浮点运算量已经非常大了。
And this flop is already pretty huge.
是63万亿次浮点运算。
It's 63t flops.
好吗？如果我们画出这些浮点运算的分布，你可以看到嵌入层，
Okay? And if we draw the distribution of these flops, you can see embedding layer,
很少，归一化很少，残差也很少。
very little, normalizing little residual little.
注意力机制，非常多，对吧？
Attention, a lot, right?
MLP，非常多。线性层，比较少。
MLP, a lot. Linear, a little.
我可以在这里可视化。这基本上就是浮点运算的分布。
I can visualize it here. This is basically the flops distribution.
然后我问同样的问题。现在，我想扩展我的语言模型。
Then I ask the same question. Now, I want to scale my language model.
主要的瓶颈会是什么？
What will be the primary bottleneck?
所以当我扩展我的语言模型时，这里的扩展是指，
So when I skill my language models away, by scanning, I mean,
我尝试增加参数数量，就像我说的，参数数量是一个强相关的函数
I try to increase lumber parameters, like I said, the lumber parameters is a strong function
边缘的值，记住，是隐藏维度。
of edge, remember, hidden dimension.
所以我尝试探索的第一个维度，当我调整我的语言模型时是
So the first dimension I try to explore, when I screw my language model is
基本上我增加了边缘的值。
basically I increase the value of edge.
所以如果我增加边缘的值，你可以看到这些项中哪一项会爆炸。
So if I increase the value of edge, you can see which of these terms will explode.
很明显，这一项是t的平方，并且它有一个非常大的常数因子，这里是32。
Apparently this term this term is t square and it has a very strong constant factor here, 32.
这一项也是t的平方，但你可以看到它的因子比这个小得多，
This is also t square, but you can see the factor is roughly much smaller than this one,
因为它是32乘以z。
because it's 32 times z.
所以如果我通过增加隐藏状态来扩展我的语言模型，
So if I skill my language model by increasing the hidden states,
这个MLP将会占用主要的计算量。
this MLP is going to take the primary, flops.
但问题是，扩展语言模型有很多维度。
But the problem is, there are a lot of dimension to skill language model.
也就是说，我尝试扩展序列长度和模型。
That is, I try to scale the sequence length and model.
所以如果我继续扩展序列规模，问题在于，你可以看到这个会减少，
So if I continue to skill sequence mass, the problem is, you can see this one will
这个也会减少，但这个会疯狂增长，
diminish this one dish one diminish, but this one will grow crazily,
因为它对我们来说是累加的，明白吗？
because it's quietive to us. Okay?
所以如果我尝试建模一个，比如说，
So if I try to start modeling a sequence less of, say,
128K 或 100万长度的序列，这部分将占用90%的算力。
128 k or 1 million, this one will take 90% of the flops.
所以你基本上把所有算力都花在了注意力机制上。
So you basically spend all your flops on attention.
是的，这就是长序列的问题。
Yeah. That's a problem of long sequence.
好的，我今天就讲到这里，希望你们回去后能深入研究，
Okay. And I think that's all I have today, and I hope you go back and dive
因为这确实是一个非常实操的内容，明白吗？
deeper because this is a pretty hands on thing, okay?
你必须能够自己操作这些内容，不用看我的幻灯片。
You have to be able to drive all this by yourself without looking at my slides.
好吗？祝你享受这个过程。好的。
Okay? And enjoy. Okay.
下一节课，我们要讲记忆。
And next lecture, we're going to do memory.
然后我们会把这三部分全部联系起来，讲瘦身法则。
And then we are going to connect all these three parts into skinny law.
好的，酷。
Okay. Cool.
嗯，嗯
H h